<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><atom:link href="https://sketchplanations.com/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><title>Sketchplanations</title><link>https://sketchplanations.com/</link><description>Explaining the world one sketch at a time</description><item><guid>https://sketchplanations.com/one-in-a-row</guid><title>One in a Row</title><pubDate>Sun, 16 Feb 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://sketchplanations.com/one-in-a-row</link><description><![CDATA[<img src="https://images.prismic.io/sketchplanations/Z6tdRpbqstJ9-e1s_SP912-OneinaRow.png?auto=format,compress&amp;w=798" /><p>Any success takes one in a row. Do one thing well, then another. Once, then once more. Over and over until the end, then it&#39;s one in a row again.</p><p>— Matthew McConaughey<br />From the book <a href="https://amzn.to/4hSHLbi" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Greenlights</a></p><p></p><p>Big things start small. It&#39;s easy to get caught up in trying to do everything at once, but you have to start somewhere. You don&#39;t need to complete the whole row today. Every sustained success starts with the first one. Sketchplanations started as one in a row.</p><p>After the first few successes, <a href="https://sketchplanations.com/the-power-of-streaks" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">the power of streaks</a> can take over. Oh, and <a href="https://jamesclear.com/second-mistake" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">never miss twice</a>.</p><p>I created a series of sketches on getting started. Find them at: <a href="https://sketchplanations.com/categories/starting" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://sketchplanations.com/categories/starting</a></p><p>Greenlights is full of fun stories. I highly recommend the <a href="https://amzn.to/4hSHLbi" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">audiobook of Greenlights</a> with Matthew McConaughey&#39;s full-of-life performance—like no other audiobook I&#39;ve listened to.</p><p></p><h2>Related Ideas to the One-in-a-Row Principle</h2><p>Also see:</p><ul><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/the-doorstep-mile" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Doorstep Mile</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/first-draft" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The First Draft is Always Perfect</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/benefits-to-you-from-getting-started" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Benefits to Getting Started</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/eat-the-frog" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Eat the Frog</a></li></ul>]]></description></item><item><guid>https://sketchplanations.com/one-buttock-playing</guid><title>One-buttock playing</title><pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://sketchplanations.com/one-buttock-playing</link><description><![CDATA[<img src="https://images.prismic.io/sketchplanations/Z6YgWpbqstJ9-Xcr_SP911-One-buttockplaying.png?auto=format,compress&amp;w=798" /><p>This week, I released a short second collection of piano-based tracks called Deep Down and Not Forgotten.</p><ul><li><a href="https://open.spotify.com/album/7fIFrkNpX7T3C2L2EI03T6?si=OQUYdqTETFSUzigjGMvjQA" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Listen on Spotify</a></li><li><a href="https://ditto.fm/deep-down-and-not-forgotten" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Listen on other Music platforms</a></li></ul><p>May I ask a favour? If you enjoy the music, would you please click to save/like on each track or the album to help others find it? Thank you. If you want to follow me as an artist that also helps.</p><p>My sketch this week is related: one-buttock playing.</p><h2>What is One-Buttock Playing?</h2><p>We all experience the power of music to move us either as players or listeners.</p><p>In his entertaining and insightful TED talk about <a href="https://www.benjaminzander.org/library/ted-the-transformative-power-of-classical-music/" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Transformative Power of Classical Music</a>, Benjamin Zander begins with a memorable sequence of imitating a child learning to play the piano. With each new year of practice, the child&#39;s playing becomes more gentle, more accomplished, and more emotional.</p><p>When playing as if an eleven-year-old, now leaning into the music, only one buttock in contact with the piano stool, Ben Zander says,</p><p>&quot;I don&#39;t know how we got into this position.</p><p>I didn&#39;t say, &#39;I&#39;m going to move my shoulder over, move my body.&#39; No, the music pushed me over, which is why I call it one-buttock playing.&quot;</p><p>He goes on to say,</p><p>&quot;You know, a gentleman was once watching a presentation I was doing, when I was working with a young pianist. He was the president of a corporation in Ohio. I was working with this young pianist, and said, &#39;The trouble with you is you&#39;re a two-buttock player. You should be a one-buttock player.&#39; I moved his body while he was playing. And suddenly, the music took off. It took flight. The audience gasped when they heard the difference. Then I got a letter from this gentleman. He said, &#39;I was so moved. I went back and I transformed my entire company into a one-buttock company.&#39;&quot;</p><h2>Reaching Flow, Getting in the Zone</h2><p>For me, one-buttock playing means going with the music, letting it take you, and being fully involved, ignoring everything else. It&#39;s like reaching a state of <a href="https://sketchplanations.com/flow" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Flow</a>, or, as in Pixar&#39;s movie Soul, being in &quot;the Zone.&quot; And as a more general metaphor, one-buttock playing is a fun reminder to give your all to an activity and be in the moment. Also, buttock is just a funny word.</p><p>There are many ways to get into Flow. You can be in Flow working on a spreadsheet. But no spreadsheet has the same effect that music can or matches how I feel when playing and composing on the piano (<a href="https://ditto.fm/deep-down-and-not-forgotten" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">have a listen</a>).</p><h2>Expertise and One-Buttock Playing</h2><p>Zander doesn&#39;t mention it in his talk, but expertise is key to one-buttock playing. The younger pianists he emulates don&#39;t experience one-buttock playing—they&#39;re too busy trying to play the damn piece properly in the first place.</p><p>One-buttock playing emerges only when they are skilful enough and know the piece inside and out. In other words, to lose yourself in the emotion or expression of a piece of music or a challenge, you must first master the craft. Once the execution is the baseline, you create space to focus on the expression.</p><p>So it is, I think, with all pursuits. Picasso could sketch with abandon because he&#39;d first mastered painting. Shakespeare could play with language because he&#39;d first mastered it. Federer could make tennis look like an art form because his mastery of the fundamentals gave him freedom on the court. A great CEO can take a company to new heights only when the team executes the basics like clockwork.</p><p><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/replicate-then-innovate" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Replicate, then innovate</a>.</p><p></p><p>You may remember Benjamin Zander from the leadership sketch <a href="https://sketchplanations.com/leading-from-any-chair" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Leading from Any Chair</a></p><h2>Related Ideas to One-Buttock Playing</h2><p>Also see:</p><ul><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/collective-effervescence" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Collective Effervescence</a>: the magic of shared experience</li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/maze-labyrinth" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Absorbing Power of a Labyrinth</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/5-ways-to-wellbeing" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">5 Ways to Wellbeing</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/forest-bathing" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Forest Bathing</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/flow" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Flow</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/match-challenge-with-skills-for-flow-at-work" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Match Challenge with Skills for Flow at Work</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/goldilocks-tasks" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Goldilocks Tasks</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/compose" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Sit Down Without Any Music</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/live-in-the-present" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Live in the Present</a></li></ul>]]></description></item><item><guid>https://sketchplanations.com/the-chinese-zodiac</guid><title>The Chinese Zodiac: Animals, Years, and Meanings</title><pubDate>Sun, 02 Feb 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://sketchplanations.com/the-chinese-zodiac</link><description><![CDATA[<img src="https://images.prismic.io/sketchplanations/Z5zV3pbqstJ9-F6s_SP910-TheChineseZodiac.png?auto=format,compress&amp;w=798" /><p>The Chinese Zodiac is a yearly cycle of 12 animals who finished first in the Jade Emperor&#39;s Great Race.</p><p>Chinese New Year 2025 marks the start of the Year of the Snake, followed by the Year of the Horse in 2026, and so on through the 12 Chinese zodiac animals.</p><p>The Chinese lunar calendar is based on the cycles of the moon—lunisolar—meaning the New Year shifts slightly each year. Also known as the Spring Festival, the New Year marks the shift between Winter and Spring. It begins on the new moon that appears between 21 January and 20 February, typically falling between late January and mid-February. Celebrations continue until the Lantern Festival, 15 days later.</p><h2>Chinese Zodiac Animals and Personality Traits</h2><p>Each Chinese zodiac sign is thought to shape the personality of those born in that year. If you were born in the Year of the Rat, you might be quick-witted and charming, while those born in the Year of the Dragon are often confident and enthusiastic.</p><p>I always forget the full list of Chinese New Year animals—it&#39;s one of those things that&#39;s beyond 7 ± 2 and just won&#39;t stick in my head. So here it is, for future reference:</p><ol><li>Rat — Charming, Quick-witted</li><li>Ox — Patient, Determined</li><li>Tiger — Brave, Competitive</li><li>Rabbit — Gentle, Compassionate</li><li>Dragon — Confident, Enthusiastic</li><li>Snake — Wise, Intuitive</li><li>Horse — Energetic, Independent</li><li>Goat (Sheep) — Calm, Creative</li><li>Monkey — Witty, Curious</li><li>Rooster — Hardworking, Observant</li><li>Dog — Loyal, Honest</li><li>Pig — Generous, Diligent</li></ol><h2>The Legend of the Great Race: Why These 12 Animals?</h2><p>The Chinese zodiac animals are from an old legend: the Great Race. The Jade Emperor, Chinese mythology&#39;s ruler of all gods, hosted a great race across a river. The first 12 animals to finish would earn a place in the Chinese zodiac calendar.</p><p>Cat and Rat, who were friends, hitched a ride on the back of Ox, who slowly swam through the river&#39;s deep water. As they crossed, Rat moved, knocking Cat into the river, but it was too dangerous to go back. As Ox neared the other bank, Rat jumped off, swimming the final metres and winning first place. Meanwhile, Dragon, despite being powerful, stopped to help others and finished fifth. Cat was left behind and finished last with a new dislike for rats.</p><h2>Variations in Other Countries</h2><p>Not all countries use the exact same Chinese zodiac signs. Vietnam, for example, swaps out two animals:</p><ul><li>The Rabbit is replaced by the Cat</li><li>The Ox is replaced by the Water Buffalo</li></ul><h2>Chinese New Year Symbols and Traditions</h2><p>Chinese New Year is full of traditions designed to bring good fortune:</p><ul><li>Red envelopes (hóngbāo) – Given to children and unmarried adults, filled with money as a symbol of luck and prosperity.</li><li>Lanterns – Hung up or released into the sky, symbolizing brightness and good fortune.</li><li>Firecrackers – Set off to scare away evil spirits and welcome the Lunar New Year with a bang.</li><li>Red and gold – The most common colours in Chinese New Year decorations, representing happiness, wealth, and good luck.</li></ul><p>Other beliefs and traditions include:</p><ul><li>washing your hair can wash out your luck for the year</li><li>giving oranges and tangerines to hosts as symbols of abundant happiness</li><li>sweeping and cleaning the house to sweep away ill fortune</li><li>decorating windows and doors with red paint, paper cutouts and banners</li><li>giving respect and honour to gods and ancestors.</li></ul><h2>Chinese Zodiac List from 2025 to 1945</h2><p>Not sure of your animal or your child&#39;s? You can find yours in this list (unless you&#39;re over 80).</p><p>If your birthday is before the Chinese New Year in January, then your animal will belong to the year before (rather like for <a href="https://sketchplanations.com/birthday-creep" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">birthday creep</a>).</p><p></p><p>2025 – Snake</p><p>2024 – Dragon</p><p>2023 – Rabbit</p><p>2022 – Tiger</p><p>2021 – Ox</p><p>2020 – Rat</p><p>2019 – Pig</p><p>2018 – Dog</p><p>2017 – Rooster</p><p>2016 – Monkey</p><p>2015 – Goat</p><p>2014 – Horse</p><p>2013 – Snake</p><p>2012 – Dragon</p><p>2011 – Rabbit</p><p>2010 – Tiger</p><p>2009 – Ox</p><p>2008 – Rat</p><p>2007 – Pig</p><p>2006 – Dog</p><p>2005 – Rooster</p><p>2004 – Monkey</p><p>2003 – Goat</p><p>2002 – Horse</p><p>2001 – Snake</p><p>2000 – Dragon</p><p>1999 – Rabbit</p><p>1998 – Tiger</p><p>1997 – Ox</p><p>1996 – Rat</p><p>1995 – Pig</p><p>1994 – Dog</p><p>1993 – Rooster</p><p>1992 – Monkey</p><p>1991 – Goat</p><p>1990 – Horse</p><p>1989 – Snake</p><p>1988 – Dragon</p><p>1987 – Rabbit</p><p>1986 – Tiger</p><p>1985 – Ox</p><p>1984 – Rat</p><p>1983 – Pig</p><p>1982 – Dog</p><p>1981 – Rooster</p><p>1980 – Monkey</p><p>1979 – Goat</p><p>1978 – Horse</p><p>1977 – Snake</p><p>1976 – Dragon</p><p>1975 – Rabbit</p><p>1974 – Tiger</p><p>1973 – Ox</p><p>1972 – Rat</p><p>1971 – Pig</p><p>1970 – Dog</p><p>1969 – Rooster</p><p>1968 – Monkey</p><p>1967 – Goat</p><p>1966 – Horse</p><p>1965 – Snake</p><p>1964 – Dragon</p><p>1963 – Rabbit</p><p>1962 – Tiger</p><p>1961 – Ox</p><p>1960 – Rat</p><p>1959 – Pig</p><p>1958 – Dog</p><p>1957 – Rooster</p><p>1956 – Monkey</p><p>1955 – Goat</p><p>1954 – Horse</p><p>1953 – Snake</p><p>1952 – Dragon</p><p>1951 – Rabbit</p><p>1950 – Tiger</p><p>1949 – Ox</p><p>1948 – Rat</p><p>1947 – Pig</p><p>1946 – Dog</p><p>1945 – Rooster</p><p></p><p>Caveat: I am not Chinese or Asian and have gathered this information from many sources over the years. Let me know if something needs correcting.</p><h2>Others</h2><p>The Chinese zodiac years are one of those things I feel like I ought to remember but always forget. Others in the same bucket for me:</p><ul><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/phonetic-alphabet" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">The NATO alphabet</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/know-your-greek-alphabet" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Greek alphabet</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/fahrenheit-and-celsius" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Celsius and Fahrenheit</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/party-bottle-sizes" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Party bottle sizes</a></li></ul>]]></description></item><item><guid>https://sketchplanations.com/snerdle</guid><title>Snerdle</title><pubDate>Sun, 26 Jan 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://sketchplanations.com/snerdle</link><description><![CDATA[<img src="https://images.prismic.io/sketchplanations/Z5NmcZbqstJ990F4_SP909-Snerdle.png?auto=format,compress&amp;w=798" /><p>How many things are much nicer than wrapping yourself snugly under the covers in bed and ignoring the world for a little longer? That&#39;s the meaning of the 18th-century dialect word Snerdle.</p><p>Snerdle (verb) is from Yorkshire dialectologist Joseph Wright&#39;s <a href="https://eddonline4-proj.uibk.ac.at/edd/" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">English Dialect Dictionary</a>. He gives the definition of snerdle, with examples, as:</p><p><strong>SNERDLE</strong>, v. [<em>snə̄·dl.</em>] To nestle closely; to wrap up comfortably in bed; to go comfortably off to sleep. “Snerdle the child up; make it comfortable.” “The children are snerdling together nicely.” “I think the baby will soon snerdle off.”</p><p>Shared by British lexicographer and etymologist <a href="https://x.com/susie_dent/status/1482326576893247492" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Susie Dent</a> in her book <a href="https://amzn.to/3EdxlnO" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Word Perfect: Etymological Entertainment Every Day</a>, snerdling suits a grey, chilly, rainy winter day—which is what we have here—or, at times, hiding from current events.</p><p><a href="https://x.com/susie_dent/status/121373987736120" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Susie also lets us know</a>: &quot;Snuzzle, snoodge, and snerdle: all verbs in the English Dialect Dictionary for snuggling under the covers as though your life depended on it.&quot;</p><p>Like snerdling? There&#39;s also the old Scottish word hurkle-durkle. Hurkle-durkling is revelling in staying in bed long after you should have gotten up. Aaah, bliss.</p><h2>More Fun Words</h2><ul><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/apricity" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Apricity</a>: the warmth of winter sun</li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/kaffikok" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Kaffikok</a>: the distance you can travel before needing a cup of coffee</li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/vorfreude" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Vorfreude: the pleasure of anticipation</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/schadenfreude" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Schadenfreude</a>: pleasure at someone else&#39;s misfortune</li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/greeble" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Greeble</a>: elements that give detail and scale and make something look more advanced</li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/word-spectrum" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Word spectrums</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/days-of-the-week" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Days of the week: the Norse gods among us</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/ordering-adjectives" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Order of Adjectives in English</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/tsundoku" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Tsundoku: acquiring books and letting them pile up without reading them</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/halfalogue" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Halfalogue: hearing half of a phone conversation</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/exercise-and-sleep" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">The virtuous cycle of exercise and sleep</a></li></ul>]]></description></item><item><guid>https://sketchplanations.com/skeuomorph</guid><title>Skeuomorph</title><pubDate>Sun, 19 Jan 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://sketchplanations.com/skeuomorph</link><description><![CDATA[<img src="https://images.prismic.io/sketchplanations/Z4f9b5bqstJ99gP7_SP908-Skeuomorph.png?auto=format,compress&amp;w=798" /><p>Why is the save icon in your software a floppy disk that no one has used for over 20 years? And that phone icon looks nothing like your mobile phone when making a call. These are both skeuomorphs.</p><h2>What is a skeuomorph?</h2><p>A skeuomorph is when a new design borrows practical elements from a former design and repurposes them in a functional or ornamental way.</p><p>Skeuomorphs are practical because they make new systems more intuitive. Their comfort and familiarity can help bridge old and new ways. For example, some electric cars are designed to look like they have air intake vents like traditional combustion cars.</p><p>More poetically, a skeuomorph can offset the loss of physical reality when interacting with our digital devices.</p><h2>Skeumorph examples</h2><p>Skeuomorphs abound in the digital world:</p><ul><li>The save icon is a floppy disk from the 1980s and &#39;90s</li><li>Microphone and speaker icons</li><li>The bin icon for deleting files</li><li>The battery icon on your computer</li><li>The envelope icon for email</li><li>Gears for Settings</li><li>Storing files in folders</li><li>Books apps displayed with bookshelves</li><li>The magnifying glass to zoom</li><li>The camera icon as a physical SLR camera</li><li>The shopping cart in an online shopping site</li><li>The &#39;desktop&#39;</li><li>Sliders and knobs, or even connecting wires, are made to look like analogue mixing desks and gear in music software (music software is awash with skeuomorphs)</li><li>A link icon represented by a link of a physical chain</li><li>A clipboard for paste</li><li>Dials and levers or a funnel representing filters</li><li>Shadows under boxes on a webpage simulate light falling on a surface to show depth</li><li>Grab bars are indications of friction points where you can change the order of a list</li></ul><p>The list goes on and on.</p><p>I once read that when designing, if you can&#39;t think of an icon for your feature in about five seconds, you probably need to write the word, as not everyone will understand it.</p><p>Not all digital icons are skeuomorphs: the printer as the print icon and the folded page for a page layout still map to their physical counterparts.</p><p>Physical skeuomorph examples include:</p><ul><li>Electric candles.</li><li>Slot machine levers that change the state of a circuit rather than spin any wheels.</li><li>Fake wood grain is used on floors or interiors.</li><li>Haptic feedback—a simulated click when pressing on a touchscreen.</li><li>Speed camera signs in the UK use a stylised visual of a classic <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kodak_Brownie" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Kodak Brownie</a> camera.</li><li>Rivets on jeans are from when fixing denim together required more than just stitching.</li><li>Electric cars sometimes include imitation air vents at the front that cool traditional combustion engines.</li><li>Car hub caps with spoke designs from early wheels.</li><li>Textured wallpaper, such as Anaglypta, echoes leather wall hangings with scored patterns.</li><li>There&#39;s even a design for an early <a href="https://spectrummagazine.org/news/adventist-pioneer-uriah-smith-envisioned-motorized-car-fake-horse-head-and-more-news/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">car with a fake horse head</a> on the front—though the inventor designed it to avoid scaring other horses on the road.</li><li>A smartwatch isn&#39;t just a watch; it&#39;s a computer you wear on your wrist.</li></ul><p>Skeuomorphs can borrow sound also:</p><ul><li>The imitation shutter sound of taking a photo on your phone</li><li>Simulated engine noise on an electric car</li></ul><h2>Skeumorphs in Software and User Interfaces</h2><p>Software and the digital domain are ripe places for spotting skeuomorphs, as they don&#39;t have physical characteristics—it&#39;s all 1s and 0s that we can&#39;t see or interact with.</p><p>Apple&#39;s early iPhone interfaces were famous for skeuomorphic elements, such as a Contacts app that resembled a contacts book complete with tabs—tabs are also skeuomorphic— and fake leather or paper effects in note apps.</p><p>Skeuomorphs, like metaphors in design, are helpful. In a magic box that can do anything—a mobile phone—a visual connection to a physical object with a defined purpose helps immediately tell you what something might be or do.</p><p>As the digital world gradually becomes the first interaction for so many uses, skeuomorphs may become less common. But we&#39;ll see them around for decades yet.</p><h2>Early skeuomorphs</h2><p>Skeuomorph is not a recent term. It was coined by archaeologist Henry Colley March by combining the Greek <em>skeuos</em> (σκεῦος) for container or tool and <em>morphe</em> (μορφή) for shape.</p><p>Skeuomorphs have been used in art and architecture since ancient times. For example, they are decorative features of stone buildings that mimic structural elements from older wooden ones, such as protruding rafters. Ancient pottery sometimes includes decorative rope patterns on the surface.</p><h2>More About Skeuomorphs</h2><p>The BBC has a lovely radio piece on <a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/sounds/play/m0002skk" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Skeuomorphs, Design, and Modern Craft</a> with novelist Will Self. The piece discusses their subtler side and some great examples, some of which I&#39;ve included here. In the same episode, they also mention the <em><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/phone-zombie" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">zombie walk</a></em> with faces lit by the glowing screen from a phone.</p><h2>Related Ideas to Skeuomorph</h2><p>Also see:</p><ul><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/affordance" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Affordance</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/common-button-states" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Common button states</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/dark-patterns" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Dark patterns</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/desire-path" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Desire path</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/fitts-law" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Fitts Law</a></li><li>&quot;<a href="https://sketchplanations.com/the-content-is-the-interface" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The content is the interface</a>&quot;—Sam Moreau</li></ul>]]></description></item><item><guid>https://sketchplanations.com/feedback-analysis</guid><title>Feedback Analysis</title><pubDate>Sun, 12 Jan 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://sketchplanations.com/feedback-analysis</link><description><![CDATA[<img src="https://images.prismic.io/sketchplanations/Z35gFJbqstJ99Kni_SP907-Feedbackanalysis.png?auto=format,compress&amp;w=798" /><p>Feedback analysis is a technique to improve judgment and discover your strengths. It could hardly be more simple:</p><ol><li>Write down what you think will happen whenever you make a key decision.</li><li>In 9–12 months, compare what you predicted against what has happened.</li><li>Repeat.</li></ol><h2>How does Feedback Analysis help?</h2><p>I learned about feedback analysis from management consultant Peter Drucker in the small Harvard Business Review read <a href="https://hbr.org/2005/01/managing-oneself" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Managing Oneself</a>. He argues that we can only make our most significant contributions when we act from our strengths. Most people don&#39;t know their strengths, so the first step is to discover them. Feedback analysis helps you do this.</p><p>Feedback analysis reveals your strengths by showing you where you are right in your predictions and which of your intended actions achieve what you hoped. It also shows you your weaknesses, where your expectations are consistently wrong, and where your actions fall short.</p><p>Drucker suggests, &quot;First and foremost, concentrate on your strengths. Put yourself where your strengths can produce results.&quot;</p><h2>The Opportunity to do What I do Best Every Day</h2><p>One of my favourite self-management reads is Strengthsfinder 2.0 by Tom Rath. It also argues that we have the most significant impact, not when we focus on fixing areas where we are weak but when we can make full use of our strengths.</p><p>The five greatest strengths I learned from that book are valuable for me to reflect on today. In fact, Sketchplanations is in some way a reflection of this:</p><ol><li><strong>Ideation</strong> – you can probably tell I am drawn to and full of ideas.</li><li><strong>Achiever</strong> - consistently creating and moving on.</li><li><strong>Relator</strong> - okay, less so this one, unless it&#39;s relating through writing and sharing. Being a relator is about building strong 1:1 relationships.</li><li><strong>Learner</strong> - I am always adding to my stock of concepts.</li><li><strong>Focus</strong> - making space to stay on task and get things done.</li></ol><p>I like to ask myself and my team members: &quot;Do I have the opportunity to do what I do best every day?&quot; Then, we get the best out of ourselves and others.</p><h2>Examples of Feedback Analysis</h2><p>Some situations where you might put feedback analysis into action:</p><ul><li>Taking a new job</li><li>Hiring a new teammate</li><li>Moving house</li><li>Getting a pet</li><li>Launching a new product</li><li>Taking a course or learning a new skill</li><li>Making predictions for your year</li></ul><h2>Write your &quot;Drucker Memo&quot;</h2><p>Dan Pink has a <a href="https://www.danpink.com/pinkcast/pinkcast-4-26-heres-peter-druckers-simple-method-for-improving-your-performance/" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">3-minute video summary</a> of this technique in his Pinkcast. He says it&#39;s useful for at least 3 reasons:</p><ol><li>It helps you see your blind spots.</li><li>It&#39;s a great way to understand your strengths.</li><li>It makes him a little bolder—after being consistently a little pessimistic in expectations, it caused him to try more new things.</li></ol><p>Dan says he takes a moment to write his expectations in his &quot;Drucker memo&quot; when beginning each new project. He then files it away and schedules a reminder in 6 months to take a look and see if his expectations are accurate. Simple.</p><p>Have you got any big decisions coming up? Maybe give feedback analysis a try.</p><h2>Related Ideas to Feedback Analysis</h2><p>Also see:</p><ul><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/panel-of-advisors" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Personal Panel of Advisors</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/ooda-loop" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">The OODA Loop</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/mistakes" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Mistakes</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/replicate-then-innovate" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Replicate then Innovate</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/the-tyranny-of-small-decisions" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Tyranny of Small Decisions</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/johari-window" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Johari window</a></li></ul><p><strong>Notes</strong></p><p>Peter Drucker is known, among other things, for coining the term &quot;knowledge worker.&quot;</p><p>&quot;I have the opportunity to do what I do best every day&quot; is one of the <a href="https://amzn.to/4h3jQp8" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">12 Elements of Great Managing</a>.</p>]]></description></item><item><guid>https://sketchplanations.com/yes-sayers-no-sayers</guid><title>Yes Sayers are Rewarded by Adventure, No Sayers are Rewarded by Safety</title><pubDate>Sun, 05 Jan 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://sketchplanations.com/yes-sayers-no-sayers</link><description><![CDATA[<img src="https://images.prismic.io/sketchplanations/Z3l_ypbqstJ99C1m_SP906-YessayersNosayers.png?auto=format,compress&amp;w=798" /><p>Improv veteran Keith Johnstone shares:</p><p><em>There are people who prefer to say &quot;Yes,&quot; and there are people who prefer to say &quot;No.&quot; Those who say &quot;Yes&quot; are rewarded by the adventures they have, and those who say &quot;No&quot; are rewarded by the safety they attain. There are far more &quot;No&quot; sayers around than &quot;Yes&quot; sayers, but you can train one type to behave like the other.</em></p><p>I can&#39;t help but put pressure on myself to be a yes-sayer. Perhaps it&#39;s the vague belief that saying yes will lead to a fuller life and range of experiences and that saying &quot;no&quot; is the easy option. And somehow, the easy option in my mind can seem like the wrong option. That&#39;s why I liked Keith Johnstone&#39;s framing for yes-sayers and no-sayers, as it clearly shows the rewards for taking either route in a decision, not just one.</p><p>If you are improvising, saying yes and accepting offers takes you to situations that may not feel comfortable but give you new experiences.</p><p>Saying no keeps you where you are. Your situation is known and safe, and you feel good for that reason.</p><p>In life, we never have to be exclusively yes or exclusively no. And it doesn&#39;t have to be white-water kayaking for yes-sayers and reading books at home for no-sayers. But certainly, there are different joys in each path. I love both: the nerves and excitement of new experiences and the comfort and safety of the known and predictable. We needn&#39;t bucket ourselves into one or the other.</p><p>An adventure, even a <a href="https://sketchplanations.com/microadventure" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">microadventure</a>, almost by definition, is the result of saying yes. And, like <a href="https://sketchplanations.com/the-fun-scale" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Type II fun</a>, it can be rewarding and fulfilling. But balancing adventure with the safety and calm of staying in one&#39;s comfort zone at times feels nice to me.</p><p></p><h2><strong>Related Ideas to Yes Sayers, No Sayers</strong></h2><p>And more improv:</p><ul><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/accept-offers" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Accept offers</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/be-spontaneous" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Be spontaneous</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/microadventure" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Microadventure</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/the-bandwagon-effect" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">The bandwagon effect</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/only-dead-fish" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Only dead fish go with the flow</a></li><li>&quot;The road to success is dotted with many tempting parking spaces&quot;—in my book <a href="https://sketchplanations.com/big-ideas-little-pictures" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Big Ideas Little Pictures</a></li></ul><p></p><p>Abraham Maslow, known for <a href="https://sketchplanations.com/maslows-hierarchy" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Maslow&#39;s Hierarchy of Needs</a>, shared:</p><p>&quot;One can choose to go back toward safety or forward toward growth. Growth must be chosen again and again; fear must be overcome again and again.&quot;</p><p>The quote is from Keith Johnstone&#39;s book <em>Impro: Improvisation and the Theatre,</em> Theatre Arts Books, 1979, as quoted in <em><a href="https://amzn.to/4h2qdc9" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Improv Wisdom</a></em> by Patricia Ryan Madson.</p>]]></description></item><item><guid>https://sketchplanations.com/ruckenfigur</guid><title>Rückenfigur</title><pubDate>Sun, 29 Dec 2024 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://sketchplanations.com/ruckenfigur</link><description><![CDATA[<img src="https://images.prismic.io/sketchplanations/Z3CJ55bqstJ983z__SP905-Ru%CC%88ckenfigur.png?auto=format,compress&amp;w=798" /><p>Ever taken a photo of a scene where someone is standing with their back to the camera, looking out at the view? That&#39;s <em>Rückenfigur</em>, a German word derived from <em>Rücken</em> (back) and <em>Figur</em> (figure), which roughly translates to &quot;figure seen from behind.&quot;</p><p><em>Rückenfigur</em> is a technique in composition where a person is included in the scene facing out to the view rather than at the viewer. It&#39;s associated with German Romantic painting and the artist Caspar David Friedrich, who painted many paintings in this style.</p><p>I like <em>Rückenfigur&#39;s</em> ability to invite you to consider the person&#39;s perspective in the scene and what they&#39;re experiencing looking out. Especially as it&#39;s often used with grand scenes from Nature, I find Rückenfigur helps me appreciate the grandeur and wonder they may feel.</p><p>When I learned about the term, I realised that I use it all the time in photography. In photos, however, I think there are other good practical reasons to employ Rückenfigur, such as:</p><ul><li><strong>Focusing on the scene</strong><br />Without showing a face, the viewer&#39;s attention is drawn to the landscape, not the individual.</li><li><strong>Adding scale and context</strong><br />A person in the frame provides a sense of size and invites contemplation from their perspective.</li><li><strong>Privacy and shareability</strong><br />Travel photos with friends or family members facing away are easier to share.</li><li><strong>No face awkwardness</strong><br />Like painting, photographing faces has a lot that can go wrong: people can have their eyes shut, be squinting, have an odd smile, no smile, bad hair...not having a visible person is more reliable.</li></ul><p>When I see a beautiful scene such as this, somehow having a person there looking out helps put me in that person&#39;s shoes and experience that wonder again. And I think that&#39;s often what I&#39;m trying to capture in a photo of Nature.</p><p>Or perhaps Friedrich started it because painting faces is hard?</p><p>The sketch is based on a photo I took in the breathtaking Jonkershoek Nature Reserve in South Africa in 2010.</p><p></p><h2>Related Ideas to Rückenfigur</h2><p>Also see:</p><ul><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/atmospheric-perspective" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Atmospheric perspective</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/the-golden-ratio" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Golden Ratio</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/hitched-to-everything-else" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Hitched to Everything Else in the Universe</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/compose-with-the-rule-of-thirds" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Rule of 3rds</a></li></ul><p><strong>Notes</strong></p><p><em>Rucksack</em> has a similar derivation translating to <em>backpack</em>.</p>]]></description></item><item><guid>https://sketchplanations.com/the-three-bricklayers</guid><title>The Three Bricklayers Story</title><pubDate>Sun, 22 Dec 2024 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://sketchplanations.com/the-three-bricklayers</link><description><![CDATA[<img src="https://images.prismic.io/sketchplanations/Z2QwVpbqstJ98rsf_SP904-The3BricklayersParable.png?auto=format,compress&amp;w=798" /><p>The Three Bricklayers’ story illustrates the power of purpose.</p><h2>What is the 3 Bricklayers Story?</h2><p>A simple version goes that a person walked past a building project and asked three workers the same question: “What are you doing?”</p><p>The first replied, “I’m laying bricks.”</p><p>The second replied, “I’m building a wall.”</p><p>And the third replied, “I’m creating a cathedral.”</p><p>The story highlights how we can view our work differently depending on whether we focus on the immediate task, the short-term goal, or the larger vision. The first worker focuses on the task at hand, the second sees the outcome of their work, and the third connects to the broader purpose of the project.</p><p>Various tellings have the first worker hunched over or working slowly. The second and third workers take increasing pride in their work, often achieving more.</p><h2>Finding Balance in Work</h2><p>There’s value in all three perspectives. There can be a lot of pride and skill in laying bricks—or whatever your equivalent task is—as well as it can be done. Setting clear, intermediate goals keeps progress on track. And someone who spends all their time looking at plans or daydreaming about what the building will become may not lay bricks as well as they need to.</p><p>To do something well, we probably need a balance of all three aspects:</p><ul><li><strong>Pride and skill in detail and craft</strong></li><li><strong>Progress through clear intermediate goals</strong></li><li><strong>Vision and meaning for our work</strong></li></ul><p>Understanding what I’m working towards and believing it’s worthwhile is a powerful motivator for me when the going gets tough.</p><p>This post isn’t really about cathedrals, but I studied the brilliant Catalan architect Antoni Gaudí in my teens. As a real-life cathedral metaphor, his incredible <a href="https://sagradafamilia.org/en/history-of-the-temple" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Basílica de la Sagrada Família</a> in Barcelona is a striking example. Gaudí’s vision for the basilica has inspired generations of artisans and workers since he took over the project in 1882. Execution, however, has been a challenge, with construction ongoing today. But that hasn’t stopped it from inspiring and drawing in visitors for decades.</p><p>I like the three bricklayers parable as a reminder that when I’m grinding on something, it helps to reconnect with the <em>why</em> behind my effort.</p><h2>Origins of the 3 Bricklayers Parable</h2><p>Like many parables, this story has been told in different forms. An early version appears in Bruce Barton’s 1927 book <a href="https://archive.org/details/in.ernet.dli.2015.262148/page/n249/mode/2up" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">What Can a Man Believe</a> (p252), featuring Sir Christopher Wren, the architect of St Paul’s Cathedral in London after the Great Fire of 1666.</p><p></p><p><em>“One morning he passed among the workmen, most of whom did not know him, and of three different men engaged in the same kind of work he asked the same question: ‘What are you doing?’</em></p><p><em>From the first he received the answer: ‘I am cutting this stone.’</em></p><p><em>From the second the answer was: ‘I am earning three shillings and six pence a day.’</em></p><p><em>But the third man straightened up, squared his shoulders, and holding his mallet in one hand and chisel in the other, proudly replied: ‘I am helping Sir Christopher Wren to build this great cathedral.’”</em></p><p></p><p>It’s hard to believe it happened, but that doesn’t mean it can’t be helpful.</p><h2>Related Ideas to the 3 Bricklayers Story</h2><p>Also see:</p><ul><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/autonomy-mastery-purpose" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Autonomy Mastery Purpose</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/the-blind-and-the-elephant" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Blind and the Elephant</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/hope" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Hope</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/flow" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Flow</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/goldilocks-tasks" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Goldilocks Tasks</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/find-your-why-not" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Find Your Why Not</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/the-story-spine" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Story Spine</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/forcing-function-for-productivity" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Forcing Function</a></li></ul>]]></description></item><item><guid>https://sketchplanations.com/panel-of-advisors</guid><title>Build Your Panel of Advisors to Ask for Advice</title><pubDate>Sun, 15 Dec 2024 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://sketchplanations.com/panel-of-advisors</link><description><![CDATA[<img src="https://images.prismic.io/sketchplanations/Z1sRmJbqstJ98bDW_SP903-Panelofadvisors.png?auto=format,compress&amp;w=798" /><p>Building your own panel of advisors is a simple technique to expand your perspectives and guide yourself through tough decisions. Think of people whose judgement and values you respect, add them to your mental panel, and when faced with a dilemma, ask, <em>&quot;What would you do?&quot;</em></p><p>While a <em>real</em> panel of advisors is invaluable, an imaginary panel has advantages: it&#39;s not limited to people you can call, and it requires no one else&#39;s time.</p><p>Your panel can include your mum, Uncle Jim, your best friend, or your high school science teacher. But why stop there? You could invite Taylor Swift, Marcus Aurelius, Eleanor Roosevelt, Abraham Lincoln, or the Buddha—famous figures whose qualities and wisdom inspire you.</p><p>Diversity is key to your panel&#39;s success, as it brings a broader range of perspectives. Uncle Jim would likely approach a problem very differently from the Buddha, and you can access both viewpoints simply by considering how each might respond.</p><p>It&#39;s curious how we can get more diverse perspectives by ourselves simply by adopting the view or mindset of someone else (as we understand them). In this way, it&#39;s rather like De Bono&#39;s <a href="https://sketchplanations.com/six-thinking-hats" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">6 Thinking Hats</a> technique. And it reminds me of my favourite research results where people generated more ideas when prompted to ideate <em>as if</em> they were a creative person.</p><p>Benjamin Franklin regularly sought to emulate his role models, as in his 13th virtue: &quot;<a href="https://en.wikiversity.org/wiki/Virtues/thirteen_virtues" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Humility: Imitate Jesus and Socrates.</a>&quot; Similarly, Napoleon Hill described meeting with &quot;Invisible Counselors&quot; in <em><a href="https://amzn.to/4foEIWI" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Think and Grow Rich</a></em> to gain insights from imagined mentors. I can&#39;t remember where I first came across this strategy but I love to put it into action.</p><p>Who would you add to your panel?</p><h2>Related Ideas to Building Your Own Panel of Advisors</h2><ul><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/rubberducking" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Rubberducking</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/groupthink" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Groupthink</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/the-bandwagon-effect" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Bandwagon Effect</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/the-abilene-paradox" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Abilene Paradox</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/design-by-committee" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Design by Committee</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/brilliance-bias" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Brilliance Bias</a></li></ul>]]></description></item><item><guid>https://sketchplanations.com/eat-the-frog</guid><title>Eat the frog</title><pubDate>Sun, 08 Dec 2024 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://sketchplanations.com/eat-the-frog</link><description><![CDATA[<img src="https://images.prismic.io/sketchplanations/Z03p9pbqstJ979dW_SP902-Eatthefrog.png?auto=format,compress&amp;w=798" /><p>Eat the Frog is a memorable, if rather gross, metaphor that means choosing the most important thing you must do today and doing that first.</p><p>It derives from a variant of a quote that Mark Twain never said, &quot;If it&#39;s your job to eat a frog, it&#39;s best to do it first thing in the morning. And if it&#39;s your job to eat two frogs, it&#39;s best to eat the biggest one first.&quot;<br />— Not Mark Twain</p><p>Another way to think about it is that if you first Eat the Frog, everything else will be easier for the rest of the day. And won&#39;t that feel nice?</p><p>The Eat the Frog time management technique was popularised in Brian Tracy&#39;s productivity book <a href="https://amzn.to/3Zh7D8N" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Eat That Frog! Get More of the Important Things Done - Today!</a></p><p>Many tools in Tracy&#39;s book are based on the general premise that there will always be more to do than you can do. So, find the things that will have the most impact and do those first. <a href="https://sketchplanations.com/rivers-and-buckets" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">The others will drift on by</a>.</p><h2>Why is Eat the Frog helpful?</h2><p>I once saw someone ask for advice on getting motivated to clean the house. One person answered: &quot;Write a book.&quot;</p><p>Sometimes, our most significant and impactful goals are those on which we so readily procrastinate. Often, these will be in the <a href="https://sketchplanations.com/the-importance-urgency-matrix" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">important, not urgent</a>, bucket.</p><p>The Eat the Frog approach helps if:</p><ul><li>You are prone to procrastination 🙋</li><li>You have a lot of things that need to be done or that you want to do</li><li>You work well in the morning</li></ul><p>One of the nice things about eating the frog first thing is that getting it done feels really good. It helps build momentum for the rest of the day with a nice endorphin rush of ticking off something significant.</p><p>Decide on your Most Important Task (MIT) to tackle, ideally the night before. If it&#39;s too big and you can&#39;t finish it in one sitting, divide it into manageable chunks. Then start on the first chunk and leave everything else.</p><p>And sometimes, the hardest thing to do is to start. So consider doing just 5 minutes. Once you&#39;ve started, very often, keeping going becomes easy.</p><h2>Challenges when Eating the Frog</h2><p>Questions that come up regularly in Tracy&#39;s book &quot;<a href="https://amzn.to/3Zh7D8N" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Eat That Frog</a>&quot;, including for the Eating the Frog principle, are variations of:</p><ul><li>What is the most important thing you could be doing?</li><li>What is the highest-value activity?</li><li>What activity will have the most impact?</li><li>If you weren&#39;t already doing this, would you start doing this?</li><li>What skills will take you furthest in your career?</li><li>What are you able to do best that others can&#39;t?</li></ul><p>It all looks pretty straightforward when I read questions like these. But I have found that answering them is usually much harder.</p><p>Our goals are often interrelated. For example, earning more may require you to increase your skills first. And getting clear on what your most important goals are first is a prerequisite and also not always straightforward.</p><p>Then, what activities are the most important or will have the most impact can be unclear. And, sometimes, small actions such as an unexpected event or connection may have out-sized benefits. Or neglecting a seemingly minor task could lead to losing a significant client. But does it still make sense to try to work on the most important task first thing in the morning? Yes.</p><h2>Don&#39;t Drag it Out</h2><p>Like a child leaving a brussel sprout at the side of the plate to get cold while they eat the roast, it&#39;s easy to leave our most impactful and daunting tasks until after the easier stuff is done. But it doesn&#39;t usually help to wait.</p><p>As the saying goes, if you have to eat a live frog, it doesn&#39;t pay to look at it for long.</p><h2>Related Ideas</h2><ul><li>Face it, you&#39;ll never get caught up, so perhaps think about Oliver Burkeman&#39;s <a href="https://sketchplanations.com/rivers-and-buckets" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Rivers not Buckets</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/the-importance-urgency-matrix" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Eisenhower Matrix: important/urgent</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/the-pomodoro-technique" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Pomodoro Technique</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/the-power-of-streaks" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Power of Streaks</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/dont-make-important-decisions-on-an-empty-stomach" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Don&#39;t make important decisions on an empty stomach</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/the-doorstep-mile" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">The doorstep mile</a></li><li><em>Eat the Frog</em> is a fantastic example of putting the principles of <a href="https://sketchplanations.com/make-your-idea-sticky" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">making your idea Sticky</a> into action</li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/get-satisfaction-and-a-clear-record-of-past-to-dos-with-checkboxes" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Use checkboxes</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/present-bias" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Present bias</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/finishing-lines" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Finishing lines</a></li><li>Poor frogs: the <a href="https://sketchplanations.com/frog-boil" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Frog boil metaphor</a></li><li>Another quote &quot;from&quot; Mark Twain appears in <a href="https://sketchplanations.com/big-ideas-little-pictures?utm_source=website&amp;utm_medium=post&amp;utm_campaign=revised-sketch&amp;utm_id=benefits-to-getting-started" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Big Ideas Little Pictures</a>: &quot;Good judgment comes from experience, and experience comes from bad judgment.&quot;</li></ul><h2>Notes</h2><p>The always excellent <a href="https://quoteinvestigator.com/2013/04/03/eat-frog/" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Quote Investigator describes the source of the Eat the Frog family of quotes</a> from the French writer Nicolas Chamfort, who said, more or less, that eating a toad first thing would help steel you against the rest of the day as nothing worse will happen to you.</p>]]></description></item><item><guid>https://sketchplanations.com/5-gift-guide-for-christmas</guid><title>The 5 Gift Guide for Christmas</title><pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2024 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://sketchplanations.com/5-gift-guide-for-christmas</link><description><![CDATA[<img src="https://images.prismic.io/sketchplanations/Z0naC5bqstJ9752F_SP901-5giftguideforChristmas.png?auto=format,compress&amp;w=798" /><p>If you&#39;re a parent or buy presents for kids, perhaps Christmas brings mixed feelings. While we love spending time with family, playing together, and taking a break, Christmas gift-giving easily brings some stress and anxiety (one of the reasons that Thanksgiving is so good).</p><p>This <a href="https://www.thepragmaticparent.com/5-gift-rule-christmas-want-need-wear-read/" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">list from Pragmatic Parent</a> is a potential antidote to the consumerism that can overtake at Christmas. The idea is to give one gift to each child in five categories: Want, Read, Wear, Need, and Do.</p><h2>8x Christmas-As-Magic</h2><p>No one wants a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NwUraEsCBjk" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Dudley Dursley on his birthday</a>, &quot;Thirty-six. That&#39;s two less than last year!&quot;</p><p>But at the same time, as a parent, you may have nostalgia for your Christmas or holidays as a child and want to create the same for your children.</p><p><a href="https://paulgraham.com/vb.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Paul Graham wrote in an essay Life is Short</a>:</p><p>&quot;Having kids showed me how to convert a continuous quantity, time, into discrete quantities. You only get 52 weekends with your 2-year-old. If Christmas-as-magic lasts from, say, ages 3 to 10, you only get to watch your child experience it 8 times. And while it&#39;s impossible to say what is a lot or a little of a continuous quantity like time, 8 is not a lot of something.&quot;</p><p>So, while, as parents, you may be working to make it memorable, at the same time, some things can easily get out of kilter. Here are some thoughts that cross our minds:</p><p>It&#39;s easy to think that we&#39;re buying more and bigger gifts each year. And we want to ensure this year&#39;s presents are as good as last year&#39;s to avoid disappointment. It&#39;s easy to look at a pile of assembled presents and think, &quot;We never had this much as kids!&quot;. And sometimes, the big ticket item we bought at great expense didn&#39;t provide nearly as much joy as racing around the house with family at Christmas. We wonder if it was really needed after all.</p><p>It&#39;s easy for Christmas gift-giving to seem out of control.</p><h2>The 5 Gift Guide: Want, Read, Wear, Need, Do</h2><p>Years ago, I learned about <a href="https://www.thepragmaticparent.com/5-gift-rule-christmas-want-need-wear-read/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">this list from Corinne at Pragmatic Parent</a>, which tries to redress some of the balance at Christmas—keeping Christmas wonder while also keeping it sane.</p><p>The idea is to get one gift in each of the 5 categories: Want, Read, Wear, Need, Do.</p><p><strong>Something I want</strong> can still be the classic Christmas big ticket item that you dream about getting as a kid. This could be a big toy, Lego set, video game, or new bike...</p><p><strong>Something I need</strong> could support a hobby, some sports equipment, a musical instrument, maybe headphones. Or it could be something they need for school—a smart set of pens or pencils or pencil case, perhaps.</p><p><strong>Something to wear</strong> is an opportunity to get something that makes them feel good daily.</p><p><strong>Something to read</strong> might be a book, magazine, comic, or subscription.</p><p><strong>Something to do</strong> could be a game, tickets to a film, a day out or visiting somewhere new.</p><p>In a later iteration of the list, Corinne added a 6th item, &quot;<em>Something for my family</em>&quot;, for an activity everyone can do together.</p><h2>A Less Materialistic Christmas</h2><p>The 5-Gift Rule for Christmas is a potential way to reduce some of the consumerism associated with Christmas and adopt a more minimalist approach.</p><p>It promotes useful gifts that won&#39;t gather dust after the excitement of the holidays has passed.</p><p>It encourages gratitude for what we receive and minimises pining for what we don&#39;t.</p><p>It also suggests gifts that create experiences for the receiver and the family—one of <a href="https://sketchplanations.com/spend-better" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">the best ways to spend our money</a>.</p><p>Full disclosure: Though we think about the list, we&#39;ve yet to adopt it wholesale. But it&#39;s a handy framework for considering different types of gifts that your children may value. It reminds us to focus on more meaningful and thoughtful gifts and experiences with less accompanying stuff.</p><h2>Related Ideas</h2><p>Also see:</p><ul><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/spend-better" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">If money doesn&#39;t make you happy, you&#39;re not spending it right</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/boxing-day" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The origins of Boxing Day</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/give-gifts-others-can-give" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Give gifts others can give</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/jolabokaflod" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Jólabókaflóð</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/pick-a-present" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Pick a present (Venn diagram)</a></li></ul><p>(<a href="https://www.gocomics.com/calvinandhobbes/1993/12/25" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Groggy parents from Watterson</a>)</p>]]></description></item><item><guid>https://sketchplanations.com/truth-and-beauty</guid><title>Discovering Truth and Beauty and Sharing it with others</title><pubDate>Sun, 24 Nov 2024 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://sketchplanations.com/truth-and-beauty</link><description><![CDATA[<img src="https://images.prismic.io/sketchplanations/Z0CkAa8jQArT1Nrx_SP899-Truthandbeauty.png?auto=format,compress&amp;w=798" /><p>This post is sketch 900 of Sketchplanations, according to my numbering. To mark that, I&#39;ve been reflecting and wanted to share what I&#39;ve learned from over a decade of this project.</p><p>It&#39;s my longest post, but I created a version you can listen to, or even watch 🙈, if you prefer. And if you don&#39;t want to listen, watch or read a long article, I hope you can just enjoy the sketch of Brenda Ueland&#39;s lovely wisdom.</p><p><a href="https://youtu.be/n8pWsaeRb8g" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Listen/watch reflections on a decade of Sketchplanations on YouTube</a></p><p></p><p>Still here? Let&#39;s go:</p><p>After the first year of one-a-day, I&#39;ve done one sketch a week, 52 a year, for over a decade without missing. I&#39;ve tried to stick to James Clear&#39;s &quot;Never miss twice&quot; rule by first not missing once.</p><p>With a few years of experience in creating and sharing under my belt, I wanted to share some thoughts about this project, about sharing your work, and about creative freedom.</p><p>I watched <a href="https://youtu.be/hwn6-8XpIuE?si=pzQ9O4lamdGLnHuU" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">a talk by Jack Conte a few weeks ago</a>. Jack is the founder of Patreon but was first—and still is—a passionate, talented musician full of energy and drive. The whole talk is interesting—he called it the Death of the Follower. But what drove me to create this was some of what he said towards the end, kind of his &quot;advice to creatives.&quot;</p><p>I want to talk about two things: The why and what of creating, and second, what sort of project a creative project should be.</p><p>I&#39;ve been lucky in so many ways with this project:</p><p>It was accidental, so I wasn&#39;t staking my future or my ego on it.</p><p>It was a side project—until this year—so I wasn&#39;t staking my paycheck and whether we could pay the mortgage and support our family on it.</p><p>And I stumbled on a simple formula that&#39;s given me great permission, licence, and scope to explore everything that interests me.</p><p>Without getting too grandiose about it, my conjured up tag line of &quot;explaining the world one sketch at a time&quot; is a huge mission, one that never really ends. But it also allows me to cover whatever aspects of our fascinating world that I want, in the way that I want.</p><p>Cartoonists also have a tremendous scope to create, but they usually have to make people laugh. Fortunately for me, I don&#39;t have to do that each time. I can cover serious things, or sensitive things, or fun things, or complex things in whichever way I want.</p><p>I&#39;m also lucky that my drawings don&#39;t have to be good. Sometimes, I look back on older ones and cringe, but usually, I don&#39;t cringe at <em>what</em> I&#39;m sharing, only my drawing of it.</p><p>Just a year or so into this project, when I complained to a good friend about not being the best artist, he simply replied, &quot;Yes, but it&#39;s the content.&quot; It really stuck with me, and it&#39;s grown on me over time. The drawings may not be as slick as other artists. Still, the content and topics I tackle are hopefully valuable, or at least interesting, in themselves. So people, I think, forgive me when I don&#39;t get it quite right and it&#39;s a bit cheesy, or my people are a bit janky.</p><p>Part of the luck in my formula is that it&#39;s become a unique collection in style and approach. The more I&#39;ve created, the more unique it becomes.</p><p>I am regularly asked how I choose and find topics to include. I only recently found the answer that really nails it.</p><p>On my website, I&#39;ve joked, &quot;Sooner or later, everything I know will be on Sketchplanations.&quot; And in some ways, that&#39;s true—at least for the useful stuff I know.</p><p>At first, sketches were a combination of serendipity in what happened to me that was interesting this week and a process of trawling through my experience and memory for the things I&#39;ve found interesting and helpful over the years. And they were also what I found myself using or thinking about regularly.</p><p>Over the years, I&#39;ve trained myself constantly to be on the lookout for topics. Sometimes I see, or read, or remember something that I instantly know I&#39;ll sketch at some point. I add it to my list, and those that I&#39;m excited about and have the clearest view on are those I tackle the next week.</p><p>But that doesn&#39;t really address the question of what makes it into the list and what doesn&#39;t. What ties these together? The answer I found most profoundly hit when I read a wonderfully opinionated book, &quot;<a href="https://amzn.to/4ezGapD" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">If you Want to Write</a>,&quot; by Brenda Ueland. Brenda says: </p><p></p><p>And what is the purpose of existence… but to discover truth and beauty and…share it with others.</p><p>— Brenda Ueland</p><p></p><p>And it was suddenly clear to me. What makes it into the list is when I&#39;ve found something that to me was a truth, an insight, an aha, a new piece of knowledge, something beautiful or fascinating that I realised. I had to feel I&#39;d discovered something. Sketchplanations has given me the wonderful vehicle to act on the impulse to share it with so many others.</p><p>I usually consider myself knowledgeable about most sketches but an expert in few. But like the age-old realisation that the teacher learns more than the students, I can tell you that there&#39;s nothing like spending a day or more a week diving into a topic, thinking how to visualise it, spending several hours sketching it and then writing about it to cement them in my own brain. I&#39;m no doubt the one who&#39;s benefited the most from this project.</p><p>It&#39;s not too long in a conversation with me before I might struggle not to interrupt with a &quot;There&#39;s a sketch for that.&quot;</p><p>And this diverse collection of 900 sketches therefore, in many ways, reflects everything I find interesting and helpful or beautiful in the world, and so is a reflection of me. In that sense it&#39;s really rather personal.</p><p>Which brings me to the second aspect of what I want to share here.</p><p>I&#39;m very lucky that many people provide suggestions for sketches they&#39;d like to see. I&#39;ve worked in design and user experience for many years. Having direct feedback of what your audience would like to see is extremely valuable. I&#39;ve tackled some of them, but too few.</p><p>I find that I&#39;m not a very good judge of sketches that will turn out to be popular—at least in the short run.</p><p>I send out new sketches each week in my newsletter. It&#39;s funny that even though I send out 10s of 1,000s of emails each month there&#39;s relatively little feedback of what people think about each new sketch.</p><p>I started posting sketches on social channels many years ago to allow more people to discover them and make it easier for people to share them.</p><p>And I post sketches on my website, so that people can find them in the future and get the answers they want when they&#39;re searching for something or looking for something to use in their own projects.</p><p>Posting on social media is interesting as, with likes, comments, shares and follower numbers I seemed to have much more feedback about whether what I did was interesting to people or not. Certainly as compared to the newsletter where there&#39;s no lightweight, low commitment way, save writing me a direct email, to let me know if it was helpful. I love receiving them by the way.</p><p>Once you start getting feedback on what seems to be popular however, you have a double-edged sword. For example, what if there&#39;s some truth or beauty that I want to share that is unlikely to be popular? Or what if there are things that will be popular that I don&#39;t find to be a truth or beauty that speaks to me or makes me want to share it.</p><p>If I was a business I think the answer is fairly clear—you create the content that your audience wants to see so people come to your site and buy your wares.</p><p>But what if a project reflects you personally? And what if it&#39;s an <a href="https://sketchplanations.com/for-the-amour-of-it" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">amateur project, created for the love of it rather than the $ of it?</a></p><p>I have tackled some sketches of topics that people asked for and that sometimes people have paid me for. What I found is that very quickly it begins to feel like a job. It&#39;s fine to do, but they&#39;re not always something that excites me.</p><p>For me, who fortunately for so long wasn&#39;t depending on it for my primary income, I found it very quickly took the joy out of the task. Why would I use my spare time—and often time from my family—to execute something that I wasn&#39;t excited about and didn&#39;t find joy in and didn&#39;t find a little spark or fire in sharing with others?</p><p>Don&#39;t get me wrong. Reaching more people with my work is great. I came round to marketing when I kept hearing &quot;Wow, I just discovered your site. I love it!&quot; 7 years after I&#39;d been working on it. These people could have been following from the beginning if I&#39;d just reached them earlier.</p><p>That was part of the impetus to create a physical book and hopefully reach a new set of people in a different way. This same feeling also drives me to work on making the website better—as the saying goes: &quot;<a href="https://sketchplanations.com/winking" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Business without marketing is like winking at a girl in the dark.</a>&quot; What&#39;s the point of having good content if people can&#39;t find it? It seems a shame.</p><p>Well, one way I could reach more people, I think of, as &quot;feeding the machine.&quot;</p><p>What I should do is find topics that have high search volume, topics that are topical or current, topics that draw a lot of engagement, topics that may be easy to grasp or share with others, and I should and do those. I should check search queries, watch what others are doing, and look for the content I post that creates the most interactions and create more content to match.</p><p>Simple messages without nuance or complexity are easy to share and take in and hit repost. But I can&#39;t bring myself to do it.</p><p>The things I keep wanting to share are my version of what Brenda called the &quot;purpose of existence&quot;—discovering truth and beauty and sharing it with others.</p><p>So I&#39;ve resisted too much of feeding the machine. I&#39;m sure it&#39;s cost me. I&#39;m sure there are a million ways I could grow my followers faster, get more subscribers, get more content engagement, exploit new channels, write traffic heavy content. But I don&#39;t want to do those if it means I can&#39;t share the truths and beauty that I find valuable.</p><p>So, at sketch 900, I&#39;m sharing these reflections as the struggles of a creator trying to understand the point and value of their project.</p><p>And to say that I plan to keep this project idiosyncratic, unexpected, and personal. Or, in some ways, <a href="https://sketchplanations.com/the-writers-in-the-writing" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">a reflection of me</a>. This will at least keep it unique.</p><p>I know that you won&#39;t find it all speaks to you—you&#39;re not me after all. But for the times when I do get it right, when you can see the truth or beauty that I&#39;m trying to share, even if it&#39;s just you and me who appreciate it, I hope that will keep it worth it.</p><p><a href="https://youtu.be/hwn6-8XpIuE?si=OzyvdIyYM0MPWNOX" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Jack Conte talks passionately and knowledgeably about the importance of building deep connections with small numbers of true fans</a>. He built <a href="https://sketchplanations.com/patreon" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Patreon</a>, through which I&#39;ve benefited so much. And a deep personal thank you to everyone who is now supporting and has supported me in the past. And I&#39;ve decided I&#39;d rather, slowly, create a deeper, more personal connection with the people, perhaps like you, who have enjoyed my project, by sharing the truth or beauty that I want to share than to feed the machine and create what the machine says is needed.</p><p>Selfishly, I hope that this will also keep it interesting for me even if it may not do the rounds of the internet as well.</p><p>Thanks everyone who&#39;s visited, enjoyed, talked about, listened to the podcast or shared my work over the years. So many of you have been generous in sharing and singing the praises of this little project.</p><p>There is of course still so much more to explain about this world. Maybe 900 is a lot of topics sketched—or maybe, I&#39;m just getting started.</p><p>Thanks for being part of the journey. See you at 1,000.</p><p></p><p>And...</p><p>If you made it this far, it&#39;d be amazing if you considered helping to get to 1,000 by <a href="https://sketchplanations.com/patreon" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">supporting me at any amount on Patreon</a> 🙏</p>]]></description></item><item><guid>https://sketchplanations.com/naismiths-rule</guid><title>Naismith's Rule for mountain hiking time</title><pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2024 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://sketchplanations.com/naismiths-rule</link><description><![CDATA[<img src="https://images.prismic.io/sketchplanations/ZzYJxq8jQArT04Li_SP899-Naismith%E2%80%99sRule-smaller.png?auto=format,compress&amp;w=798" /><p>Naismith&#39;s Rule provides a quick estimate for hiking time in the mountains, intended for &quot;easy expeditions.&quot; It suggests:</p><ul><li>1 hour for every 3 miles (5km) walked</li><li>+1 hour for every 2,000 ft (600m) of ascent</li></ul><p>For example, suppose your hike covers 6 miles with 2,000 ft of ascent. In that case, Naismith&#39;s Rule suggests allowing 3 hours total—2 hours for distance and 1 hour for elevation.</p><p>(Here&#39;s a <a href="https://images.prismic.io/sketchplanations/Zz38Ba8jQArT1FFN_SP899-Naismith%E2%80%99sRule-metric-smaller.png?auto=format,compress" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">metric sketch of Naismith&#39;s Rule</a>)</p><h2>Origins of Naismith&#39;s Rule</h2><p>William Naismith was a Scottish Mountaineer born in 1856. He spent years trekking in the Highlands and was, to be fair, probably made of nails. In the <em>Scottish Mountaineering Club Journal</em> in 1893, he wrote:</p><p>&quot;...a simple formula, that may be found useful in estimating what time men in fair condition should allow for easy expeditions, namely, an hour for every three miles on the map, with an additional hour for every 2,000 feet of ascent.&quot;</p><p><a href="https://simrich.ams3.digitaloceanspaces.com/SMCJ/Number%207%20to%2012%20-%20Vol%20%202%20-%201892-1893.pdf" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Scottish Mountaineering Club Journal, Vol. II, September 1892, No.3, p.136</a> (pdf)</p><h2>Does Naismith&#39;s Rule Work?</h2><p>A figure I learned that&#39;s stuck with me is that a brisk walk is around 4 mph. But that&#39;s actually pretty fast and wouldn&#39;t apply on a mountain trail and certainly not hiking up a mountain. So I&#39;ve run into the challenge myself when planning a trip in the mountains of how to guess how long a hike will likely take.</p><p>From a recent hike—where I made sure to run through the full <a href="https://sketchplanations.com/kitchen-table-survival-skills" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">kitchen table survival skills</a> and <a href="https://sketchplanations.com/the-10-essentials" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">10 essentials</a> before leaving—limited daylight was a safety consideration. So knowing how long the hike might take was really important. Incidentally, there&#39;s a rule of thumb, literally, for <a href="https://sketchplanations.com/rules-of-thumb-for-remaining-daylight" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">estimating remaining daylight</a>.</p><p>Lots of people have put Naismith&#39;s Rule to the test, including me, and though it&#39;s a slightly optimistic metric, it&#39;s a starting point. On my recent hike, we were slightly over, but not by much.</p><h2>Adjusting Naismith&#39;s Rule</h2><p>To adjust for your circumstances, add time for:</p><ul><li>Tricky or technical terrain and trail condition</li><li>Steep descents</li><li>High altitude</li><li>Lunches and snack stops</li><li>Not being &quot;in fair [physical] condition&quot; in the view of a rugged mountaineer from Scotland in the 1890s</li><li>Heavy packs, poor weather</li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/the-automation-paradox" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Getting lost</a></li><li>Walking with children</li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/prints-and-performances" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Photography</a>, <a href="https://sketchplanations.com/everyones-a-geek-about-something" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">bird watching</a>, animal spotting</li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/atmospheric-perspective" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Time to stop and enjoy the views</a></li><li>The size of your group—I have heard the rule of thumb to add 15 mins for each person in your group</li><li>Sitting and sketching</li><li>Presumably, if the hike was really long, you&#39;d slow down</li><li>The Unexpected</li></ul><p>So, there are many reasons why Naismith&#39;s Rule may be on the light side. But it&#39;s a decent place to start from.</p><h2>Killian Jornet Laughs in the Face of Naismith&#39;s Rule</h2><p>Someone for whom Naismith&#39;s Rule definitely doesn&#39;t apply is the incredible <a href="https://www.instagram.com/kilianjornet/" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Killian Jornet</a>, whom I watched in the beautiful documentary <a href="https://www2.stage.netflix.com/gb/title/81469443" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Déjame Vivir</a> on Netflix. Footage of him running along knife-edge ridges at the top of the Alps is breathtaking. In 2024, he hiked all 82 peaks above 4,000m in the Alps in 19 days without using motorized vehicles between them 🤯.</p><h2>Lock-Miles</h2><p>I was told about the term lock-miles, a kind of Naismith&#39;s Rule but for canal journeys rather than hikes. To estimate the journey time, you&#39;d first calculate the lock-miles with the idea that it takes as long to travel through a lock as it does to travel a mile.</p><p>A journey of 10 miles with 5 locks would be 15 lock-miles. For experienced boaters, a typical speed might be 3 lock-miles an hour, so the journey of 15 lock-miles would take 5 hours.</p><p></p><p>Let me know if you give Naismith&#39;s Rule a try!</p><p></p><p>Prefer metric? So do I. Here&#39;s a <a href="https://images.prismic.io/sketchplanations/Zz38Ba8jQArT1FFN_SP899-Naismith%E2%80%99sRule-metric-smaller.png?auto=format,compress" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">metric Naismith&#39;s rule</a> (with the approximate rounding)</p><p></p><h2>Related ideas</h2><p>Also see:</p><ul><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/the-fun-scale" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Fun Scale</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/the-10-essentials" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">The 10 essentials</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/kitchen-table-survival-skills" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Kitchen table survival skills</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/take-photos-of-maps" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Take photos of maps before a hike</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/use-a-compass-with-a-map" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Use a compass</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/rules-of-thumb-for-remaining-daylight" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Rule of thumb for remaining daylight</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/kaffikok" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Kaffikok — the time you can travel before needing another cup of coffee</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/time-hierarchy" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Time hierarchy</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/isochrones" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Isochrones</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/our-senses-are-built-to-take-in-information-at-human-pace" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Human pace</a></li></ul><p>I made some <a href="https://www.redbubble.com/shop/ap/166339534?asc=u" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">prints and products with</a> and <a href="https://www.redbubble.com/shop/ap/166340322?asc=u" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">without the text</a> in case, like me, you like a peaceful mountain ridge without any rules</p>]]></description></item><item><guid>https://sketchplanations.com/the-paradise-paradox</guid><title>The paradise paradox</title><pubDate>Sun, 10 Nov 2024 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://sketchplanations.com/the-paradise-paradox</link><description><![CDATA[<img src="https://images.prismic.io/sketchplanations/Zy9mdq8jQArT0p7l_SP898-Theparadiseparadox.png?auto=format,compress&amp;w=798" /><p>The Paradise Paradox is the tempting but misguided belief that moving to a &quot;paradise&quot; will magically make everything better. It&#39;s the idea that a change of scene to somewhere beautiful or exciting will somehow sweep away all our problems. And while a fresh setting can give us a lift, the reality is often more complicated: paradise, as wonderful as it might be, won&#39;t always solve the everyday challenges we bring along with us.</p><h2><strong>Idealizing Paradise</strong></h2><p>Moving to your paradise might feel incredible, and it&#39;s a life-changer for some people, but it&#39;s easy to idealize paradise, imagining it as a place where worries simply disappear. Yet even the most stunning places could start to feel ordinary, and your conceptualised paradise may have its own challenges.</p><p>For instance, perhaps your paradise is a beautiful, distant, exotic land. Such a paradise, however, has the drawback of no longer being distant or exotic once you arrive and the day-to-day takes over. Someone living in a fast-paced metropolis might dream of calm and quiet, while someone surrounded by calm and quiet may dream of the rush and excitement of the big city.</p><p>Alastair Humphreys, who introduced me to the Paradise Paradox in his book <em><a href="https://alastairhumphreys.com/local/" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Local</a></em>, gave a great example in our <a href="https://podcast.sketchplanations.com/microadventures-with-al-humphreys/" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">podcast about Microadventures</a>. In an interview on an American podcast, the interviewers couldn&#39;t imagine exploring Kansas to be exciting—it was known or even home to them. But to Alastair, a visit to Kansas would be an adventure, full of new things to see and do. It&#39;s a reminder that our ideas of paradise are often fueled by novelty—and novelty, by nature, doesn&#39;t last forever.</p><h2><strong>Expectations, the day-to-day, and Adaptability</strong></h2><p>Some of the Paradise Paradox may be explained by how easy it is to build up expectations. If we imagine paradise as the ultimate fix, it could lead to disappointment if it doesn&#39;t live up to the dream. As for <em><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/vorfreude" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">vorfreude</a></em>—the joy of anticipation—the build-up can sometimes overshadow the reality.</p><p>Then there&#39;s the simple truth that day-to-day life in paradise isn&#39;t a vacation. A tropical beach holiday lets you unwind and enjoy the scenery without a care. But living there might mean dealing with rainy seasons, work deadlines, or just regular old laundry.</p><p>Humans are also remarkably adaptable. We&#39;re good at adjusting to new surroundings, which means something initially remarkable may soon become the new normal. It&#39;s a bit like the grass-is-greener mentality we see in many areas of life. If you&#39;re a consultant, you might long for the stability of an in-house role, while in-house folks might crave the variety of consulting.</p><h2><strong>The Dark Side of the Paradise Paradox</strong></h2><p>In some cases, the Paradise Paradox takes on a more serious tone. The documentary film <em><a href="https://www.paradiseparadoxfilm.com/" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Paradise Paradox</a></em>, executive produced by Olympic ski racer Bode Miller and filmmaker Brett Rapkin, explores how people drawn to the beauty and tranquility of US mountain towns sometimes face mental health struggles. These picturesque communities, though visually idyllic, have experienced higher-than-average rates of suicide, highlighting the challenges of living in remote, isolated settings.</p><h2><strong>Strategies to Minimize the Pull of the Paradise Paradox</strong></h2><p>To reduce the effect of the Paradise Paradox, it helps to focus on what brings fulfillment in any setting, allowing us to appreciate where we are without feeling the constant pull of an imagined paradise. Here are a few ways to lessen the allure:</p><p>1. <strong>Cultivating Gratitude</strong></p><p>Practicing gratitude allows us to recognize the value of what we already have. Focusing on the positives around us may make us less inclined to search elsewhere for happiness, realizing that contentment often lies closer than we think.</p><p>2. <strong>Prioritizing Experiences Over Material Goods</strong></p><p>Research consistently shows that <a href="https://sketchplanations.com/spend-better" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">experiences bring longer-lasting happiness than possessions</a>. Prioritizing meaningful activities and memories can bring joy and satisfaction, outlasting the initial thrill of accumulating more.</p><p>3. <strong>Simplifying Life</strong></p><p>A minimalist approach can help reduce the constant desire for more—whether it&#39;s things, places, or achievements. Simplifying our lives can allow us to focus on what truly matters and bring a greater sense of peace.</p><p>4. <strong>Pursuing Meaningful Goals</strong></p><p>Focusing on personal growth, nurturing relationships, and contributing to our communities can offer a lasting sense of fulfillment that doesn&#39;t depend on our surroundings. Meaningful goals and connections often provide the depth of happiness that location alone can&#39;t bring.</p><p>Paradise can certainly refresh us, but true and lasting happiness is often about embracing where we already are and what we already have.</p><p></p><p>Since writing this I keep seeing related quotes:</p><p>The only Zen you can find on the tops of mountains is the Zen you bring up there.</p><p>— Robert M. Pirsig (via <a href="https://dynamic.wakingup.com/quote/QTF1761" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Waking Up</a>)</p><p></p><p>“We tend to attribute happiness to our circumstances (what happens to us) but studies suggest our happiness is really dependent on what we pay attention to.”</p><p>— Cal Newport, <a href="https://calnewport.com/deep-work-rules-for-focused-success-in-a-distracted-world/" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Deep Work</a> (via <a href="https://www.mindovertech.com/" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Mind Over Tech</a>)</p><p></p><p>&quot;Happiness isn&#39;t getting what you want, it&#39;s wanting what you got.&quot;</p><p>— Garth Brooks</p><p></p><p><a href="https://quoteinvestigator.com/2020/11/22/where-you-go/" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Wherever you go, there you are.</a></p><p></p><p>Also see:</p><ul><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/the-paradox-of-choice" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">The paradox of choice</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/the-transparency-paradox" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">The transparency paradox</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/the-fresh-start-effect" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">The fresh start effect</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/vorfreude" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Vorfreude</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/5-ways-to-wellbeing" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">5 ways to wellbeing</a></li></ul>]]></description></item><item><guid>https://sketchplanations.com/isometric-projection</guid><title>Isometric projection</title><pubDate>Sun, 03 Nov 2024 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://sketchplanations.com/isometric-projection</link><description><![CDATA[<img src="https://images.prismic.io/sketchplanations/ZyTZVa8jQArT0HlP_SP897-Isometricprojection.png?auto=format,compress&amp;w=798" /><p>Isometric projection is a simple way to draw 3D shapes. The meaning of isometric is &quot;equal measure,&quot; from the Greek words <em>iso-</em> for equal and <em>metric</em> for measure. So, in an isometric drawing, all three axes, x, y, and z, are scaled equally, giving a clear, undistorted view of an object in three dimensions.</p><p>Except that isometric drawings can look a little odd and oversimplified. This is because of the lack of perspective, a visual distortion of 3D shapes we experience in the real world. In a perspective drawing, parallel lines converge in the distance towards a vanishing point, but in an isometric drawing, parallel lines stay parallel, and sizes don&#39;t get smaller in the distance.</p><p>The lack of perspective in an isometric view can make it look artificial, but it always looks clear.</p><p>I learned isometric drawing when studying engineering. Armed with a stack of isometric paper with a printed isometric grid, we had to reel off exercises involving drawing isometric views of 3D objects. And isometric projection is really handy for this. It can take a long time to build the skills to sketch a realistic 3D-looking object, perspective and all, but with isometric paper, you can quite quickly produce something that communicates to you or others what&#39;s in your head or on the workbench.</p><p>Isometric projection is handy for boxy shapes—I chose an approximation of the Bauhaus Dessau building by Walter Gropius to show it. If you need curves and angles, just like with perspective drawings, it can help to draw more boxes around these areas and use them to align your curves and meeting points for your lines.</p><p>Isometric views and their variations have had somewhat of a resurgence of late in video and board games. It turns out they&#39;re pretty helpful in map-based or city-building games such as Zynga&#39;s Farmville, Civilisation, or Sim City as the isometric view allows all parts of a scene to be viewed equally—in the distance or up close—while still seeing every detail in, say, a building, wherever it is.</p><p>If you want to try some isometric drawings, making your own isometric grid paper is easy. Just draw equally-spaced vertical stripes and then a criss-cross of lines in both directions at 30 degrees from the horizontal. This gives a host of equilateral triangles and an easy base to start drawing your 3D objects. Or just download some templates online. You&#39;ll find that building up more complex shapes out of cubes is dead simple if you keep to the lines on the isometric grid.</p><p>Just as in the drawing here, sometimes shapes drawn in isometric view lend themselves to curious optical effects. The lack of perspective can make the difference between heights and depths ambiguous. So, you can&#39;t always tell if two surfaces are at very different heights or if one is in the distance. The brilliant puzzle game <a href="https://www.monumentvalleygame.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Monument Valley</a> uses this quirk of isometric projection to create mind-bending puzzles that are well worth a try. For instance, rotating a high surface can suddenly make a platform that extends far into the distance 🤯.</p><p>Isometric-like projection can also help make impossible shapes, such as the <a href="https://sketchplanations.com/impossible-staircase" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Impossible Staircase, or Penrose stairs</a>. Another type of projection, <a href="https://sketchplanations.com/anamorphosis" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">anamorphosis</a>, creates a drawing that only looks correct from a particular viewpoint. Anamorphosis leads to some remarkable street art.</p><p></p><p>Also see:</p><ul><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/two-and-a-half-dimensions" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">2.5D objects</a>, including an old video of me drawing a sketchplanation</li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/orthographic-projection" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Orthographic projection</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/one-point-perspective" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">One-point perspective</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/two-point-perspective" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Two-point perspective</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/three-point-perspective" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Three-point perspective</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/atmospheric-perspective" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Atmospheric perspective</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/anamorphosis" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Anamorphosis</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/impossible-staircase" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Impossible Staircase, or Penrose stairs</a></li><li>When drawn nice and faint, the isometric grid is an example of a <a href="https://sketchplanations.com/ghost-grid" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">ghost grid</a></li><li>Isometric projection is quite the opposite of &quot;<a href="https://sketchplanations.com/draw-what-you-see-not-what-you-think" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">draw what you see, not what you think</a>.&quot; Foreshortening can be hard to get the hang of.</li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/life-is-3d-give-edges-thickness" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Life is 3D—give edges thickness</a></li></ul>]]></description></item><item><guid>https://sketchplanations.com/fight-or-flight</guid><title>Fight or Flight</title><pubDate>Sun, 27 Oct 2024 16:48:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://sketchplanations.com/fight-or-flight</link><description><![CDATA[<img src="https://images.prismic.io/sketchplanations/ZxkcSYF3NbkBX8TM_SP896-FightorFlight.png?auto=format,compress&amp;w=798" /><p>The fight-or-flight response is our body&#39;s automatic and ancient response to perceived threats or danger. This innate physiological response in animals and humans prepares us to either confront a threat (fight) or flee from it (flight). This mechanism, often referred to as entering fight-or-flight mode, likely played a critical role in our survival.</p><h2><strong>Face to face with a tiger</strong></h2><p>At the annual Wildlife Photographer of the Year Awards, I saw an astonishing photo of a tiger surprising workers in a field (<a href="https://www.awazthevoice.in/india-news/wildlife-activist-nejib-ahmed-says-man-animal-conflict-is-alarming-18085.html" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Tiger Run by Nejib Ahmed</a>). Everyone is in flight mode except one man, much braver than me, who perhaps through instinct has stood to fight, staring down the approaching tiger with a long stick. The photo is captivating in its drama and struck me as a perfect fight-or-flight example in action. Thankfully, no one—including the tiger—was hurt in this instance.</p><p>The adrenalin that can flood our bodies during such moments may sometimes give us strength to do what we didn&#39;t expect, surprising ourselves with what we are capable of—Nicola Morgan, when discussing <a href="https://amzn.to/3NCnyt5" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">the amazing teenage brain</a>, gives an example of her leaping a 5ft fence and looking back with amazement. Sudden strength or speed like this is a well-known fight-or-flight symptom.</p><h2><strong>Reptilian brain, Lizard brain</strong></h2><p>The fight-or-flight response is linked to theories about how different parts of the brain developed during our evolution. Modern research has corrected some aspects of this idea, but the basic concept remains.</p><p>The most primitive parts of the brain—those we may share with, say, dinosaurs—are responsible for automatic behaviours like protecting territory, aggression, fear and fending off danger. This is often referred to as the reptilian brain or lizard brain. These brain areas are key to our survival instincts and play a critical role in activating fight-or-flight mode.</p><p>Years of evolution since then have given us brain structures like the limbic system, which is responsible for our emotions and social behaviours. The amygdala, part of the limbic system, is especially important in triggering fear and the fight-or-flight response.</p><p>Later, the neocortex evolved, enabling humans to assess threats rationally, solve problems, and make decisions—giving us more control over how we respond to fear or anxiety.</p><p>The response, also illustrated by the snake rearing up in the sketch, is a fallback to our oldest instincts from the oldest parts of our brain when faced with a threat, so the theory goes.</p><h2><strong>Freeze, Flight, Fight, Fright</strong></h2><p>Fight-or-flight psychology, coined by physiologist Walter Cannon in 1915, is only part of a broader spectrum of acute stress responses. A more accurate sequence we experience may be <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0033318204701619" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">freeze, flight, fight, or fright</a>.</p><p><strong>Freeze:</strong> Our immediate reaction to danger might be to &quot;stop, look, listen,&quot; remaining hyper-vigilant while we assess the threat, and perhaps hope by not moving, the dinosaur won&#39;t spot us.</p><p><strong>Flight:</strong> We may flee the situation to safety.</p><p><strong>Fight:</strong> If escape isn&#39;t possible, we might fight back, as shown by the brave individual in the tiger photo.</p><p><strong>Fright:</strong> This might include panic and immobility, playing dead in case a predator decides we&#39;re not worth eating after all.</p><p>As you see, the updated list continues with excellent alliteration, which no doubt helped make the <a href="https://sketchplanations.com/make-your-idea-sticky" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">idea sticky</a> in the first place (other proposals add fawn, faint, flock and more).</p><h2><strong>When Fight-or-Flight Doesn&#39;t Help</strong></h2><p>While the tiger scenario shows our ancient brain instincts at work, most modern-day situations don&#39;t involve life-or-death threats. However, we may still enter fight-or-flight mode during stressful, anxiety-inducing moments, such as public speaking, a challenging work interaction, or a difficult conversation.</p><p>In these cases, our age-old reactions may not serve us well. The same ancient brain that would help us survive a predator may now cause us to avoid daunting tasks. Whether it&#39;s a work presentation, a cold sales call, or confronting a personal issue, we may feel the urge to retreat from the action and get a snack from the kitchen instead.</p><p>When our ancient instincts—so finely tuned for survival—are no longer serving us in modern situations, it&#39;s helpful to pause and let our higher-order thinking take the lead. Techniques like <a href="https://sketchplanations.com/box-breathing" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">box breathing</a> or meditation help calm the body and mind, allowing us to move beyond fear and resistance. By doing so, we can overcome the automatic urge to &quot;fight or flight,&quot; or even freeze or fright, and instead respond with clarity, control, and confidence.</p><p></p><p>Also see:</p><ul><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/box-breathing" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Box breathing</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/the-spotlight-effect" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">The spotlight effect</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/dont-make-important-decisions-on-an-empty-stomach" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Don&#39;t make important decisions on an empty stomach</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/cognitive-overhead" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Cognitive overhead</a></li><li>See <a href="https://sketchplanations.com/big-ideas-little-pictures" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Big Ideas Little Pictures</a> for Melissa Dahl&#39;s Awkwardness Vortex and the technique of reframing anxiety as excitement</li></ul>]]></description></item><item><guid>https://sketchplanations.com/leading-from-any-chair</guid><title>Leading from Any Chair</title><pubDate>Sun, 20 Oct 2024 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate><link>https://sketchplanations.com/leading-from-any-chair</link><description><![CDATA[<img src="https://images.prismic.io/sketchplanations/Zw-NJoF3NbkBXf1s_SP895-Leadingfromanychair.png?auto=format,compress&amp;w=798" /><p>Leading from Any Chair is the idea that we all have the opportunity to influence the action even when we&#39;re not standing at the front. It&#39;s a principle for effective leadership and teaching yourself and others to lead.</p><h2><strong>The Art of Possibility</strong></h2><p>In their inspiring book, <a href="https://amzn.to/3Y0vyZu" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Art of Possibility</a>, Benjamin and Rosamund Zander relate a story from renowned violist Eugene Lehner, who played in the Kolish Quartet and Boston Symphony Orchestra. One day, in an interpretation class led by Zander with Lehner as a guest coach, Ben Zander asked him, &quot;How can you bear to play day after day in an orchestra led by conductors, many of whom must know so much less than you?&quot;</p><p>Lehner said he was playing in a rehearsal in his first year in the orchestra when the conductor, Koussevitsky, struggled to lead the orchestra as he wanted through a tricky Bach piece. A friend of Koussevitsky and fellow conductor, Nadia Boulanger, was sitting in on the session. Koussevitsky stopped and asked if Nadia would conduct the passage so he could hear what it sounded like from the back of the hall. Nadia conducted the passage without a hitch, and the rehearsal continued. But the episode left Lehner ever wondering and waiting for the moment when a conductor might say to him, &quot;Lehner, you come up here and conduct. I want to go to the back of the hall and hear how it sounds.&quot;</p><p>&quot;It&#39;s now 43 years since that happened,&quot; said Lehner, &quot;and it is less and less likely that I will be asked. However, in the meantime, I haven&#39;t had a single dull moment in a rehearsal as I sit wondering, &#39;What would I say to the orchestra, should I suddenly be called upon to lead?&#39;&quot;</p><h2><strong>Stepping up to lead</strong></h2><p>There are many occasions when I have personally grappled with whether now is the moment to step up and lead. Sometimes, I have taken them. Other times, I feel ashamed that I sat back and let events unfold without contributing.</p><p>It&#39;s the easy path to defer to whoever&#39;s leading and consider that there may be better times to influence or say what you think needs to be said. Or you can take the view that we&#39;re all responsible in some way for what we&#39;re experiencing, and we all have the opportunity to influence for the better.</p><p>You don&#39;t have to be the captain on the field to influence your fellow players.</p><p>A typical example I&#39;ve experienced is seeing a presenter struggle in a meeting, perhaps with technical difficulties or audience confusion. It may take only a little to try and help with the tech or to <a href="https://sketchplanations.com/ask-the-question" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">ask the presenter to explain a point that you see needs to be clarified</a> for people. Or, as an audience member, you can sit back and consider it not your problem.</p><p>Once, in the middle of a performance at a wedding, the music suddenly clicked off for the performer. Immediately picking up on the problem, the wedding photographer started singing the melody, picking up where the music left off. Getting the idea, all the guests joined in, continuing the music to the end. This quick intervention undoubtedly led to a better show for everyone, including the performer.</p><h2><strong>Learning to lead</strong></h2><p>When you choose to step up, it&#39;s an opportunity to learn to lead. You may discover that there&#39;s more to leading than it seems and gain empathy for the leaders around you.</p><p>By constantly asking myself, &quot;What would I say should I suddenly be called upon to lead?&quot; I am mentally rehearsing for when I am needed, for when I am in the position of a leader. It speeds up my learning and keeps me always ready for action.</p><p>It&#39;s one reason why always <a href="https://sketchplanations.com/start-three-mindmaps-at-conferences-and-workshops" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">thinking of questions at a talk or conference</a> is valuable. It forces you to engage with the material, and when the opportunity arises, you&#39;re ready to step up and ask about what matters to you or what everyone is thinking.</p><h2><strong>Identifying passion and the leaders in front of you</strong></h2><p>As a leader, if you believe you are superior, for example, as the conductor who doesn&#39;t consider the orchestra members to have anything to contribute to the interpretation of the music, then you are likely to suppress the voices of the very people you need to deliver.</p><p>People want to contribute—that&#39;s why they attended the class, joined the company, or trained in their discipline. Rosamund Zander advises that, as a leader, we can train ourselves to spot the passion of the people in our teams. We can actively look for occasions to allow team members to lead. And if we don&#39;t see the passion, we can ask ourselves, &quot;Who am I being that they are not shining?&quot;</p><h2><strong>Leading from Any Chair</strong></h2><p>We can learn to lead at any time. So the next time you&#39;re just one in a crowd, consider that you can lead from any chair. Ask yourself, &quot;What would I say if I were suddenly called upon to lead?&quot;</p><p>--</p><p>In case it wasn&#39;t clear, I highly recommend <a href="https://amzn.to/3Y0vyZu" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Art of Possibility</a>, which I listened to as an audiobook read by Benjamin and Rosamund. And I always recommend finding 20 mins to watch <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=r9LCwI5iErE" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Benjamin Zander&#39;s classic TED talk, The Transformative Power of Classical Music</a>. Left-buttock playing is a sketch I&#39;ve been planning for a long time.</p><p></p><p>Also see:</p><ul><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/ask-the-question" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Ask the question at talks</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/start-three-mindmaps-at-conferences-and-workshops" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Mindmap at conferences</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/authority-to-information" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push authority to information</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/whose-job-is-it" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Responsibility Poem: Whose job is it?</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/the-accountability-ladder" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The accountability ladder</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/autonomy-mastery-purpose" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">What drives us: Autonomy, Mastery, Purpose</a></li></ul><p></p><p>This is the last time I plan to draw an orchestra. I now know a little of what it must feel like to draw Where&#39;s Wally?</p>]]></description></item><item><guid>https://sketchplanations.com/eponym</guid><title>Eponym</title><pubDate>Sun, 13 Oct 2024 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate><link>https://sketchplanations.com/eponym</link><description><![CDATA[<img src="https://images.prismic.io/sketchplanations/Zwaoa4F3NbkBXFMe_SP894-Eponym.png?auto=format,compress&amp;w=798" /><p>An eponym is a word named after somebody or someplace.</p><p>An eponym, almost by definition, comes with a story, making them some of the most intriguing words. Knowing what an eponym is also allows you to use the word eponymous, which is always a good way to sound smart.</p><p>Some of my favourite eponyms are now commonplace products that took the inventor&#39;s name. Some examples:</p><h2><strong>The Rubik&#39;s Cube</strong></h2><p>The Rubik&#39;s cube is an invention by Hungarian architecture professor Ernő Rubik. The cube has the fascinating property of being a solid object that&#39;s also fluid.</p><p>This year (2024), the <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2024/07/01/science/rubiks-cube-puzzles.html" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Rubik&#39;s Cube turned 50</a>, celebrating around half a billion cube sales, scores of speed-cubing championships, and documentaries. When Rubik first invented the cube, he wasn&#39;t sure it was solvable and only managed it for the first time several months after creating it.</p><p>In 2020, Rubik told the story of the cube in his book, <a href="https://amzn.to/4dzMv2U" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Cubed: The Puzzle of Us All</a>.</p><p></p><h2><strong>The Jacuzzi</strong></h2><p>The fabulously named jacuzzi, or more generally the hot tub, is named after the Italian Jacuzzi family. The seven brothers of the family—there were also six daughters—trained to become engineers, making plane propellers, irrigation systems and pumps before one of the brothers created a homemade bath to help his two-year-old son who was suffering from rheumatoid arthritis. The rest, as they say, is history.</p><p>Saskia Solomon tells some of the brothers&#39; story, which includes the court case Jacuzzi vs Jacuzzi, and the invention of the jacuzzi in the 2023 New York Times article, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2023/08/11/style/the-frothy-saga-of-the-jacuzzi-family.html" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Frothy Saga of the Jacuzzi Family</a>.</p><p></p><h2><strong>The Sandwich</strong></h2><p>After so long as what seems the most basic of foods, it was remarkable for me to learn that the humble sandwich was named after a person: John Montague, the 4th Earl of Sandwich. Though he probably spent most of his time in London, the title itself is associated with the small town of Sandwich in Kent, in Southeast England.</p><p>The story goes that the Earl liked playing cards and wanted food he could eat without having to leave his game and that wouldn&#39;t give him sticky fingers that would damage the cards. Incarnations of open sandwiches appeared much earlier elsewhere. For example, the trencher—something I had to look up when reading Game of Thrones—involved serving food on top of old bread as a sort of plate. But it took the Earl&#39;s dedication to card playing, or at least desk work, to take the next step many years later.</p><p></p><h2><strong>The Biro and BiC ballpoint pens</strong></h2><p>László Bíró was a Hungarian-Argentine inventor who created the first truly successful ballpoint pen. In the US, the BiC is more common, an eponym this time from Marcel Bich.</p><p>It&#39;s said that Lázló experienced his fountain pen leaking from heat—fountain pens being very common before the ballpoint—and was inspired by a printing press that used a cylinder to spread the ink. All it needed was to go in all directions. Enter the ballpoint.</p><p>While the invention seems obvious in hindsight, perfecting it for robust, commercial use was challenging. For example, finding suitable ink for the tiny ball bearing to spread, which doesn&#39;t leak or clog and isn&#39;t overly affected by heat. Lázló teamed up with an aviation company—who use a lot of ball bearings—which also provided a great use case of finding a pen that wouldn&#39;t leak from the air pressure changes in planes. Later, BiC licenced the technology from Biro. A <a href="https://www.moma.org/collection/works/82141" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Bic Cristal® Ballpoint pen is part of the collection at the MoMA</a>.</p><p></p><h2><strong>Silhouette</strong></h2><p>I only learned that silhouette was an eponym while preparing this sketch, but it&#39;s perhaps the best of all.</p><p>Étienne de Silhouette, a French government finance official tasked with curbing a French deficit in the 1700s, unwittingly gave his name to the classic black-on-white simple outline image of a person. His severe frugal policies of taxes, curbing royal spending and even melting down gold and silverware earned him the reputation of doing things cheaply. Hence, a cheap method of creating a portrait, cutting out black paper and laying it on a white background, became known as a silhouette.</p><p></p><h2><strong>Diesel</strong></h2><p>Nearly everyone will recognise the fuel that Rudolf Diesel gave his name to and his diesel engine. Diesel created a breakthrough engine that was more efficient than typical steam engines while being smaller and weighing less.</p><p>Curiously, I learned that Diesel died in mysterious circumstances, disappearing on a journey across the English Channel in 1913.</p><p></p><p>--</p><p></p><p>An excellent <a href="https://99percentinvisible.org/episode/the-eponymist/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">episode of the 99% Invisible podcast featuring Helen Zaltzman of the Allusionist</a> raised several interesting questions about eponyms I hadn&#39;t considered. Here are a few to think about:</p><ul><li>Eponyms are common in medicine, for example, when we name a disease or condition after those playing a part in the discovery. However, the name, for example, Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease, tells a medical practitioner very little about the disease compared to a name that relates to the symptoms of the sufferer or the cause. Should examples like these be replaced with more practical names?</li><li>Eponyms almost always have a way of oversimplifying a story, often wrapping up complex histories with the names of white males. For example, rarely are products invented or diseases identified solely through the actions of one person. Yet an eponym chooses one, or some people, at the expense of others.</li><li>Eponyms may be the name of someone later discredited or who develops a tarnished reputation from other actions in their lives. Should someone who did evil deeds be remembered in an eponym or should it be changed?</li></ul><p></p><p>Who knew eponyms could be so interesting?</p><p></p><p>Know some good eponyms with fun stories? I&#39;d love to hear them.</p><p></p><p>Eponyms are distinct from the fun concept of <a href="https://sketchplanations.com/nominative-determinism" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Nominative determinism</a>—an aptronym—where someone&#39;s name seemingly influenced their future actions or career choices (for example, Les McBurney — Volunteer firefighter).</p><p></p><p>I&#39;ve covered a lot of eponyms over the years, far more than I realised. Using the handy list page on the site, I&#39;ve collected some other <a href="https://sketchplanations.com/categories/eponym" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">eponym examples</a>, which include a lot of my favourites:</p><ul><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/blooms-taxonomy" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Bloom&#39;s Taxonomy</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/bortle-scale" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Bortle Scale</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/braille" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Braille</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/campbells-law" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Campbell&#39;s law</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/chestertons-fence" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Chesterton&#39;s fence</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/conways-law" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Conway&#39;s Law</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/dracula-sneeze" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Dracula sneeze</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/dunbars-number-150" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Dunbar&#39;s number: 150</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/fahrenheit-and-celsius" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Fahrenheit and Celsius</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/fitts-law" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Fitts&#39; Law</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/goldilocks-tasks" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Goldilocks tasks</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/goodharts-law" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Goodhart&#39;s Law</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/hanlons-razor" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Hanlon&#39;s Razor</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/hofstadters-law" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Hofstadter&#39;s Law</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/identify-a-douglas-fir" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Identify a Douglas fir</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/jevons-paradox" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Jevon&#39;s Paradox</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/johari-window" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Johari window</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/koomeys-law" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Koomey&#39;s Law</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/kano-model" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Kano model</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/marchettis-constant" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Marchetti&#39;s constant</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/maslows-hierarchy" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Maslow&#39;s hierarchy of needs</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/metcalfes-law" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Metcalfe&#39;s Law</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/mobius-strip" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Möbius strip</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/moores-law" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Moore&#39;s Law</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/muphrys-law" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Muphry&#39;s Law</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/pyrrhic-victory" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Pyrrhic victory</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/russells-teapot" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Russell&#39;s Teapot</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/sankey-diagram" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Sankey diagram</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/scoville-scale" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Scoville scale</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/spoonerisms" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Spoonerisms</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/strahler-stream-order" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Strahler stream order</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/the-abilene-paradox" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Abilene paradox</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/the-barnum-effect" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Barnum effect</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/the-betty-crocker-effect" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Betty Crocker Effect</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/the-boaty-mcboatface-effect" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Boaty McBoatface effect</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/the-diderot-effect" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Diderot Effect</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/the-doppler-effect" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Doppler Effect</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/the-droste-effect" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Droste effect</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/feynman-learning-technique" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Feynman Learning Technique</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/the-gartner-hype-cycle" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Gartner Hype cycle</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/the-generalised-peter-principle" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Generalised Peter Principle</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/gini-coefficient" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Gini coefficient</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/the-goldilocks-zone" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Goldilocks Zone</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/the-ikea-effect" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The IKEA effect</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/the-keeling-curve" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Keeling curve</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/the-lake-wobegon-effect" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Lake Wobegon Effect</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/the-lucretius-problem" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Lucretius problem</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/the-mercator-projection" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Mercator projection</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/the-monty-hall-problem" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Monty Hall problem</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/the-overton-window" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Overton Window</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/oxford-comma" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Oxford comma</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/the-peter-principle" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Peter Principle</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/the-plimsoll-line" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Plimsoll line</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/the-pomodoro-technique" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Pomodoro Technique ®</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/the-rashomon-effect" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Rashomon effect</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/the-rosetta-stone" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Rosetta Stone</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/the-shirky-principle" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Shirky Principle</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/the-streisand-effect" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Streisand Effect</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/stroop-test" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Stroop test</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/veblen-goods" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Veblen goods</a></li></ul><p></p><p>Other fun -<em>onym</em> words about words:</p><ul><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/acronyms-and-initialisms" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Acronyms and initialisms</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/capitonym" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Capitonym</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/heteronym" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Heteronym</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/homonyms-homographs-homophones-heteronyms" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Homonyms, homographs, homophones… </a></li></ul><p></p>]]></description></item><item><guid>https://sketchplanations.com/vorfreude</guid><title>Vorfreude</title><pubDate>Sun, 06 Oct 2024 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate><link>https://sketchplanations.com/vorfreude</link><description><![CDATA[<img src="https://images.prismic.io/sketchplanations/Zv6FOLVsGrYSwVWb_SP893-Vorfreude.png?auto=format,compress&amp;w=798" /><p>Vorfreude is a delightful German word for the pleasure of anticipation. It combines <em>vor</em>, meaning &quot;before&quot; or &quot;in advance&quot;, and <em>freude,</em> meaning &quot;happiness&quot;. It&#39;s the joy from the anticipation of joy.</p><p>How to get more happiness from the same activity? Vorfreude!</p><h2>The magic of Vorfreude</h2><p>For me, the magic of Vorfreude lies in how it stretches out the pleasure of any upcoming event or experience. Once I hit &#39;Confirm&#39; to book a trip, it kicks off joy for months whenever I think about the trip. And the great part about it, if we&#39;re organised, is that a trip in December can bring &#39;anticipatory joy&#39; from when we book it in January. I need only reflect on my positive feelings about the trip, and life seems better.</p><h2>&quot;Vorfreude is the best joy&quot;</h2><p>I&#39;ve often found that the Vorfreude may surpass the joy of the actual trip. With my Vorfreude glasses on, I never worry about the mosquitoes, the heat, or the inevitable waiting on the journey.</p><p>Germans have a saying that reflects this: &quot;Vorfreude ist die schönste Freude,&quot; or Vorfreude is the best joy.</p><p>Thanks to something called <a href="https://sketchplanations.com/fading-affect-bias" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">fading affect bias</a>, the emotional weight of negative memories tends to fade faster than positive ones. This leaves us with a rose-tinted view of past trips and may conveniently erase the niggly parts we didn&#39;t enjoy, allowing us to focus on just the good parts of a trip coming up. Or perhaps it&#39;s our <a href="https://sketchplanations.com/optimism-bias" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">optimism bias</a> (we had a <a href="https://podcast.sketchplanations.com/optimism-bias/" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">fun podcast about optimism bias</a>).</p><h2>Vorfreude is not just for the big events</h2><p>Vorfreude doesn&#39;t only apply to big events like a holiday or wedding. I find anticipatory joy in small things, too. I look forward to the first coffee in the morning every day. Sometimes, the coffee won&#39;t live up to what I&#39;d hoped for, but hey, I&#39;d already been enjoying the idea of it <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/C1xomhZJqn9/" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">since I finished my last coffee the day before</a>.</p><p>I look forward to meeting friends and loved ones. I look forward to a dinner out. I look forward to weekends. I look forward to the next football match. I look forward to a cake coming out of the oven. Many people look forward to 5 o&#39;clock each day. By simply reflecting on these moments of future joy, we can experience happiness right now, no matter where we are.</p><h2>Enhancing Vorfreude</h2><p>We can even work to cultivate and enhance our Vorfreude. As a child, nothing built anticipation like an advent calendar, ramping up excitement for Christmas day as I opened each new window. Sharing photos of your holiday destination with friends and family before you go and planning activities increases vorfreude. Getting good things in the diary can kick us out of <a href="https://sketchplanations.com/languishing" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">languishing</a>.</p><p>In some ways, Vorfreude mirrors the benefits I get from fear-based training plans or the <a href="https://sketchplanations.com/forcing-function-for-productivity" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">forcing function</a> of signing up for endurance events later in the year—having signed up for the event, I start to benefit from it as soon as I get out training with friends.</p><h2>The opposite of Vorfreude</h2><p>Of course, you may not be looking forward to the trip that&#39;s coming up. Perhaps upcoming events are filling you with dread. Anxiety is an emotion perhaps closest to the opposite of Vorfreude, or anticipatory anxiety more specifically.</p><p>I&#39;ve also seen <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/simonleadbetter_haveabreak-chillax-holiday-activity-7248980503750406144-S2oX" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer"><em>Vorangst</em> proposed</a>—with Angst being strong anxiety or fear—which seems a very suitable alternative.</p><h2>Avoiding expectations</h2><p>While thinking fondly about upcoming events can give you Vorfreude, a reader pointed out to me the dangers of thinking too much about how good something will be in the future.</p><p>It&#39;s easy to slip into setting expectations in your mind about how good something ought to be. If it then doesn&#39;t live up to your expectations, it could affect your enjoyment in the moment.</p><p>I guess the sweet spot is expectation-free Vorfreude.</p><h2>Voorpret</h2><p>It&#39;s not just the Germans who thought of giving a word to the joyful anticipation and excitement before an event. The Dutch use the word <em>Voorpret</em> for the same concept—<em>pret</em> meaning fun.</p><h2>Enjoy the moment</h2><p>But don&#39;t forget to enjoy the moment. I&#39;m sometimes reminded of <a href="https://www.gocomics.com/calvinandhobbes/1992/06/18" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Calvin talking with Hobbes about the enjoyment of his favourite breakfast cereal</a>, Chocolate Frosted Sugar Bombs:</p><p><em>&quot;Ahhh, another bowl of chocolate frosted sugar bombs! The second bowl is always the best! The pleasure of my first bowl is diminished by the anticipation of future bowls, and by the end of my third bowl, I usually feel sick.&quot;</em></p><p>While it’s great to savour the anticipation, <a href="https://sketchplanations.com/if-this-isnt-nice-i-dont-know-what-is" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">remember to enjoy the moment</a> when it arrives.</p><p></p><p>More tips for Vorfreude in this excellent article by Rachel Dixon: <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/2024/apr/09/the-vorfreude-secret-30-zero-effort-ways-to-fill-your-life-with-joy" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Vorfreude secret: 30 zero-effort ways to fill your life with joy</a></p><p></p><p>Also see:</p><ul><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/schadenfreude" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Schadenfreude</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/fading-affect-bias" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Fading affect bias</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/5-ways-to-wellbeing" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">5 ways to wellbeing</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/wabi-sabi" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Wabi sabi</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/if-this-isnt-nice-i-dont-know-what-is" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">If this isn&#39;t nice I don&#39;t know what is</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/choose-passwords-that-make-you-happy" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Choose passwords that make you happy</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/maslows-hierarchy" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Maslow&#39;s hierarchy of needs</a></li><li><a href="https://sketchplanations.com/spend-better" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">If money doesn&#39;t make you happy you&#39;re probably not spending it right</a></li></ul><p></p><p>I made prints for this as:</p><ul><li>the <a href="https://www.redbubble.com/shop/ap/165284322?asc=u" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">full Vorfreude sketch</a></li><li>a <a href="https://www.redbubble.com/shop/ap/165308709?asc=u" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">simpler vorfreude picture with text</a> (which works rather well as a message on a clock)—to be honest, this is probably better =)</li><li>and just the <a href="https://www.redbubble.com/shop/ap/165311449?asc=u" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">umbrella and beach</a></li></ul>]]></description></item></channel></rss>